Good morning. I'm Purian, a research associate from Q.
This is joint work with Nikki Nicholson and the APNIC team at Q.
I'm going to be talking about a pipeline we've built that uses large language
models for nomenclature extraction and...
Good morning. I'm Purian.
Good morning. I'm Purian. Good morning. I'm Purian.
Good morning. I'm Purian, a research associate from Q.
This is joint work with Nikki Nicholson and the APNIC team at Q.
Hello, everyone. I am Yagmur. I work at
OGSL as a programmer analyst. I develop
AI-powered applications,
especially for extracting information from...
Hello, everyone. I am a strategic partner with thesis,
non-profit documents, and field notes.
Good morning, everyone. I'm Yasin Bakis from
Tulane University, Biodiversity Research Institute.
And today's session is about
LLMs in
biodiversity data
specifically. And we are going to answer, can
LLM extract biodiversity information?
And more important
questions are, how reliable is that extraction going
to be? And can we determine
where the information came
from?
Can our uncertainty be determined
or represented accurately? And can the results
be connected to structured
standards,
as in Darwin Core,
Odoban Core kind of standards? And then how should
humans remain involved
in validation and creation
of this process? I uploaded my entire speech so that we
can have more time
for the speakers for the Q&A and discussion sessions.
So you can find it on the chat session.
We will start with our first speaker, Vince Smith.
Okay, good morning, everybody.
So congratulations on making the 8:30 slot on the last day of the
conference. I have to say, I sometimes don't make this slot, so well done.
So I want to start really with some really big questions.
So things like how do we move data to
evidence to action and do this at really big
scale? How do we do this with a constantly evolving
dataset where there's new records coming, maybe 10,000,
20,000 records a day, sometimes even an hour, as we move towards
more automated monitoring?
How do we do this with a constantly evolving set of
questions that we have for that data, that sometimes we can't
predict, sometimes with real urgency with which we need
to answer those questions?
How do we do this with provenance so that we can see the
attribution chain as that data moves from that foundational
level
right the way through to synthesis and action with that
data?
And of course, perhaps critically, how do we do this sustainably?
And I mean that across all the different dimensions of sustainability.
So not just ethical sustainability and sort of green sustainability, but
also financial sustainability. And we've seen in
this conference over the past few days, some real challenges
with how we sustain our community and our infrastructures
financially. So tackling these kind of questions, in my
view, these are probably some of the biggest questions that we've got in the
discipline, and this needs some really big thinking.
And fortunately, again, we've seen a number of fantastic sessions throughout
the week that are really trying to tackle this.
And when we, within the Natural History Museum first started to think about this,
we really started to think about,
well, what would be the kind of infrastructures that would
actually solve these kind of problems?
And obviously,
AI, and particularly machine learning, is utterly transforming
our landscape in terms of how we approach answering these
questions. So we've got enormous
examples again this week of how machine learning is extracting
information,
and spotting trends in our data, and then how
large language models are beginning to make inference and link that
data up in ways that truly were unimaginable.
And I think the big thing for me is simply the scale, the
ambition by which we can now have for our data has
truly transformed. And again, for those of you who've come to TADWIG over
regular years, probably the last three years has seen
more innovation in this space than perhaps the last 10.
And that's really because AI is utterly transforming
this landscape So a few years ago now, we started to think,
well, how could we bring this story together?
How could we bring that enormous totality of all that
fragmented data across these huge repositories, and
what would be the kind of infrastructure that we might need to
build to solve these problems? And we had this rather
crazy dream with this insanely ambitious title, A
Planetary Knowledge Base, to bring that story
together. And very crudely, various iterations of this slide have
existed over the past few years, but this is essentially the
sum, if you like, totality of that vision.
Which is how we take our big data infrastructures holding
information about people, observations, collections,
institutions,
genetic data, literature. How do we align all of
that data? What AI tooling will we need to basically connect
that data up? And at the time when we first were thinking about this, we were
heavily invested in knowledge graphs, and indeed still are.
But also we've got foundation models now, and
these large language models derive from those foundation models, which are
allowing us to integrate and synthesize that knowledge and
basically potentially reason statistically across them.
But also then we've got this enormous capability to start to
build services off the back of all of that
enormous data. But the scale of this is
truly intimidating. The sheer volume of data, the
sheer compute capacity, the size of some of these graphs
is truly scary. So one of our challenges was
how do we chunk this problem up into
manageable projects that we could actually start to deliver real
value,
but do this in a way that at the same time started to tackle what we think
is this big, overarching architecture that solves these really
big,
visionary global challenges. And in effect, we broke
this problem up into a series of phases, and we're very much at
phase one. So this is still very much an emerging infrastructure.
But we broke it up into a series of projects that started to tackle
some really profound issues for things like the Biodiversity
Heritage Library, for digitization, and also something I'll come on
to talk about called the Museum Digital Backbone.
So Biodiversity Heritage Library basically encompasses almost the
totality of the sum of digitized literature that we have.
Of course, it's not complete because it very much is focused on that heritage
literature, but it's been a great place to start.
And those of you who saw Hiris Ghu's presentation earlier this
week will have seen how we're basically trying to build a new
discovery layer for BHL, which extracts
institutional names, taxa, specimens, chunks,
articles,
and we're working closely with Mistral, who have--
We've ReOSI-ed almost the entirety of BHL now, and we
are extracting those entities. And this is forming the
backbone for what we call the literature layer of
the planetary knowledge base.
Another big, very practical problem that we have, and one actually that
you're going to be hearing about from Ariana very shortly,
is how do we digitize at scale and extract and
transcribe all the entities that we have in
our things like our card indexes, our specimen labels, our
herbarium sheets, where much of that information resides in
analog form. I won't spoil the surprise of what
Ariana's going to be talking about next, but just to say that
Scribe has been our solution to that.
And again, this is helping us with that knowledge extraction piece for the
planetary knowledge base.
And then the last thing, and those of you who are invested in big
institutions like me at the Natural History Museum in London, there's always
a challenge of how do you deliver institutional value on these
projects. It's not just about core research, it's about how can we deliver
value closer to home. And one of the things is we sit on
vast repositories of data that sometimes we can't
share, in some cases for very good reasons.
Things like grant proposals, for example.
Things like the archive of publications that our scientists have
built. And so we've been building something we call the Museum Digital
Backbone, which is essentially a sort of miniaturized
version of this knowledge graph and LLM.
We've actually tried to accelerate it using a tool out of the box called
Amazon Quick, which is sort of designed to help
institutions and organizations do this thing very quickly.
And we're using it to help pull data for
publications, to pull data for writing grants,
to help our own scientists accelerate their research internally.
So the overall architecture of this is,
we're now just at the point where we're starting to think about all these different
layers taking us from that source evidence to those series of
services. But mindful of time, I just want to focus on a few
key design principles. And one that's been absolutely central
to this vision is how we track attribution and benefits
through that value chain from source evidence right the way
through to the services that we build.
And then how do we return that value to the communities that
have actually proportionately contributed to it?
And this has led to a series of literally
design principles that are kind of baked into our thinking about how we
deliver this. So critically, we want to preserve those
evidence layers at every step by basically making use
of all the identifiers, all of the provenance, all of the
licenses that are baked into that data.
We want to proportionally make all the contributions that people have
made to
surfacing these datasets. We want to make that visible through
attribution, and then we want to share those benefits And
maybe most controversially of all, we want to look at
what remuneration models might be appropriate to deliver
those benefits back to the wider community.
The ambition here is not that we're building some infrastructure just
for one institution. This is very much a vision for a
global infrastructure which is community led.
We have a series of use cases that I'm running out of time, I think, to go
into deeply, but particular areas of interest are actually
around biodiversity change. So how do we synthesize metrics from
all of this data that track that change?
And also, how do we use those commercially to generate revenue?
We have some examples of that already within the Natural History Museum with the
Biodiversity Intactness Index that we work with Bloomberg
to literally sell that data source to.
But we're trying to use the planetary knowledge base of the sort of tooling that
we're building to accelerate the production of those metrics.
We're also looking at areas like big pharma, which have a deep
interest in our data, but also, quite controversially,
have
not necessarily particularly strong sort of ethical practices.
So we're trying to work with them. And then I'll wrap up now because I can see our
moderator has stood up. Really just to acknowledge the fact that there are many
people working on this,
and there's a whole team behind it, but also to emphasize we're hiring
a new AI engineer at the moment. So if you're interested in coming to the museum
and working on this, do come and talk to me. Thanks for your time.
Thank you, Vincent. We can have a couple of questions. You have time still.
Okay.
So you mentioned provenance and attribution.
During the plenary session, we had a couple of talks about data sovereignty and
care.
Do you think that this kind of massive data mobilization at scale can
be aligned or reconciled with care principles?
That is a tough one, and actually it's probably the A of care, the
authority to control, that I think is maybe the most difficult within the
community and certainly within the big institutions.
So I think there's a cautionary yes
to that. I think, so for example, the kind of models that we're
talking about here where if we can proportionally represent
indigenous communities whose contributions to these
datasets generate value, then what we're proposing
is a model whereby we can return some of that benefit
in a way that, frankly, is far more tangible than some of the other
implementations of care that I have seen. Can we do it?
Frankly, I don't know, because these are huge
research challenges. So those of you in,
I forget the name of the session yesterday, but dug into this some
more, these are big research problems about basically fair
AI and how we deploy that. So maybe.
Vince, there's a big AWS-shaped box in
the middle of this-
Yes
... which sort of screams proprietary enclosed.
Do you want to elaborate on that? Is that fear warranted?
No. It's a great question, though, so thank you for that.
So frankly, we have to work with big tech with this.
We're struggling
with the sheer scale of this. So if it's not AWS, it's going to
be Google, or it's going to be Azure, or it's going to be one of the other
big tech organizations. And frankly, we shouldn't be
fearful of working with those organizations.
We do have to approach that ethically and carefully.
So AWS have been a great supporter in terms of providing financial,
and technical support for this vision, and we need to lean into
that as a community, but we do need to do it eyes wide open.
Thank you, Vince.
Our next speaker is going to be Ariana Saleily-James,
if I pronounce correctly.
Yeah.
I'll just go this way.
Hey.
Hello. Oh, wow, that's loud. Okay.
Thank you for having me, Tadhg. I'm here to talk about a project called Scribe.
Just before I start, I want to apologize in advance.
I'm not that organized, so just after this talk, I'm going to have to shoot off and
pack my suitcase and check out of my hotel.
But I will be back, so I can always answer
questions before the next session.
Anyways,
before we go on to Scribe, I wanted to take you guys down a
trip down memory lane to talk about some previous projects on
data extraction.
So
if you remember Alice, does anyone here remember Alice?
Again, shout out to Sean for being involved in making it.
So Alice is a great
digitization setup we have at the Natural History Museum.
My involvement on it was on extracting the label data.
So being able to
look at images taken with Alice and
find where the labels are, merge the labels together so you have clean versions of
each labels, and then that will then go into a transcription tool.
So back when we were testing this, we were using tools such as Tesseract and other
OCR tools,
and that was in Tadhg 2022, if anyone remembers that.
Okay, the next data extraction tool that we were working on was also with
videos. So I've got two examples here.
They might play. Will they play? Oh, yeah, you can see one of them slowly moving.
So this was also inspired by Alice, whereas with Alice we
had the images, but here we thought, "What about videos?" And
these tests were done with large language models, and I know my colleague Jack
Hollister also did similar tests within his robotics workflow.
So we've got one video here showing label tracking.
So finding the label on the specimen, then tracking the label,
sorry and then that will then go into an LLM or OCR pipeline.
And the video on the right is actually taken from video,
from NIBIO, if you were at my talk on Tuesday.
Okay, next one is a different
data extraction project that we were working on.
Shout out to Douglas Russell and Ken Norris from the
museum. This was based on extracting data from standard egg
cards.
This was a pretty big project where we were-- I just realized there's a screen
here, so I don't need to turn around.
So this was a pretty big project where we were testing how to extract
data in a structured format. So not just transcribe it, but have that
categorized as well. So we were using tools such as Google Vision, and
we were also testing other OCR tools to transcribe the text and
automatically structure the text.
And this worked well for us. We had accuracies of over 90% for all of
the categories that we had extracted.
And if anyone remembers that, I spoke about that in TADWIG 2024 in Okinawa.
And then after that, we turned to more LLM-based projects.
We had lots of projects with different collections, whether it
was looking at collection registers, again, using LLMs to extract
data from those, looking at
specimen labels again, so this time a little bit bigger than the insects.
We looked at other vertebrates. At the top there you've got some labels from
the bird skin collection, so shout out to Alex Bond and Claire
Atkinson for that project.
Also herbarium sheets, so colleagues like Harris were working a lot on
using LLMs as part of the PKB for data extraction.
Also, we worked on slightly more complicated cards where there was information both
on the front and back. So how do you systematically extract data
from those and have it inputted in the same row?
But the point here is that though we had a lot of projects, they were all
separate projects. So we had a workflow for the egg
cards. We had a workflow for the bird skins.
We had a workflow for herbarium, for the paleontology cards we have,
for the registers. They were all separate workflows.
They were all trained separately. They all had different prompts.
So it was fun for me because I got to work with lots of different collections at
the same time, but it probably was not the most efficient way of doing
it.
So this leads us to SCRIBE. So what is SCRIBE?
I was going to ask you guys to guess what it stands for.
For the eagle-eyed out there, you might have seen what it stood for in Vince's
slides, but this is what SCRIBE stands for.
Also, shout out to Vince, because I'm pretty sure you came up with this acronym for
us. We do love an acronym at NHM UK, I must say.
Also, I just said NHM UK. So yeah. So SCRIBE stands for
Structured Collection Records Interpretation and Bio-Entity
Extraction. So quite a mouthful, but it has a cool acronym.
So what is it? So the idea with SCRIBE is to just have one
platform, so one global platform where users can upload
their images of their datasets and get a structured output out
of it. So the key word here is the word
structured. So we're not planning on using this for, say,
transcribing historical books, for example. Thank you.
So we are after information that can be outputted in a structured
format. Now, your data doesn't need to look structured to begin with.
So some of those specimen labels may not look as structured, there might not be
unity amongst them, but you can extract structured information from there, such as
locality, habitat, et cetera.
And the goal here isn't necessarily the extraction of data.
That's the wider goal. The goal is the development of that tool.
So that is the SCRIBE program. And the SCRIBE program
is mainly funded by DCMS, which is a
UK government department,
but also funded by a private donor.
And it is going to be LLM and computer vision based.
And I think that's it. I will add, so you've already heard from Vince that
the data extracted from SCRIBE will then integrate with the PKB, so work that my
colleague Harris is doing, and also the digitization part of this will
feed directly into DISCO UK aims.
So firstly, who are the SCRIBE team?
So quite a medium-sized team for
DGI standards at the museum. So myself, I'm the project lead on
here, so if anyone spotted Rachel, I will try and embarrass her if she's
here. So Rachel is the AWS lead here.
Ben is the SRO. Ginger Burns is the technical leadership.
We recently hired Ahmed Jafar Usman Ahmed, who's my
data scientist, and we are very soon to hire our software
engineer. So that is the
team at NHM, but it's not just us because it's always important to work
with those who actually know the data better than we do.
So we've got a bunch of stakeholders as well.
So we've got internal stakeholders consisting of curators and others
who work with collections and other datasets, and we also have external
stakeholders. We've got the DCMS folks and the donor folks, but we're also in
discussion with other DISCO UK institutions.
Now,
SCRIBE is in its very early stages.
Ahmed joined us in August, and it's now the end of September, so
very early stages, but we're hoping to get this project done by
March 28. So that's the end of the project.
But I'll give you a quick overview of workflows that we've planned
or workflows that we have semi-tested. None of this is set in stone, of course.
So I chose the brightest green. Goodness me.
So the idea is you have this website, and you want to
upload your images. Now, first, we want to make it as simple as
possible. We don't want to ask you guys too many questions.
We don't want to make you write too many things down.
So we do ask a couple, though. So first question is,
does your dataset that you've uploaded, is it going to contain a
mixture of different datasets? Do you have
a dataset containing 100 images of the same-looking card, or do
you have a mix where you've got herbarium sheets, labels, everything all in one go?
Now, the reason why we ask that is we can still handle it.
We're just going to handle it slightly differently.
If you do say if you have a singular type, then great.
We come up with a prompt for that dataset.
If not, we actually do some clustering, which I'll get into later in
order to separate your dataset.
As part of DISCO UK, we're also hoping to give partner
institutions a certain amount of tokens so they can
use our platform for free, up to a certain limit, of course.
And then after that, folks will have the option of adding their own API key.
We also want to specify what type of format that you're looking for.
Things like JSONs and CSVs are examples of formats.
And then you do the extraction. That's where the magic happens.
You download your dataset. You specify if you're interested in
sharing that dataset with us. If you say yes, it might feed into PKB
stuff and other DISCO UK stuff again.
And then, yeah, enjoy your structured dataset.
So run extraction. I'll just talk a little bit about that as well.
So again, this is just a very preliminary workflow.
So the think-- Thank you. The thinking is that we will do some
pre-processing of the images first.
This may include auto rotations and things like that.
Then there's the clustering stage I spoke about, where if you've uploaded data
where your datasets, there is a lot of variation within the dataset, within the
structures, within the types, we do some clustering on that first.
Once you've done your clusters, we select some samples from those clusters.
If you only have one cluster, then we still select some samples, and for
that sample, we will run a quick LLM check to see what
entities are there. And we do that so we can develop a customized prompt.
So there will be a base prompt developed, but those extra entities help
us just customize that prompt even more.
And then after we've got that customized prompt is when we run the LLM
extraction on the entire dataset.
Now from there, you'll do some data cleaning, of course, and then
potentially some formatting that to Darwin Core standards if
it's happening in this stage.
So we've done some recent tests on this.
I know I said we only hired our data scientist in August, but we have been
working on this for a while. I've had a few students working on similar projects as
well. I don't know if you guys were there for Phoebe Santos' talk on Tuesday, but
she gave a great talk on different
LLM comparisons as well. So I had-- Oh, sorry,
almost done. So we've done some tests on clustering, for example, looking at
tools like DBSscan and even basic things like principal
component analysis and being able to cluster images.
We've also done tests on auto cropping, so aligning everything, so even if your
image is too zoomed out or anything, we've got tools to
fix that. Same with rotation as well.
We've also done tests on different LLMs.
So in this example, I've just shown you some of the closed weight models, not the
open weight models. But these are just small, closed weight model comparisons that
we've done on the minis and the lights, which is quite interesting.
And we've done tests on handwritten versus printed and typed as well because we get
a lot of questions from curators saying, "What about handwritten things?" And our
results show that they
did equally well with the LLM analysis.
So the training data-- I promise I'm almost done, guys.
So the training data we have is quite broad.
We've got a range of different collections there, vertebrates, invertebrates,
botanical collections as well. Don't think we have any fungi, actually.
So if you guys have fungi data to share with me, I'm very happy to include that
as well.
We did put a call out to other DISCO UK institutions.
So we've got data not just from the Natural History Museum UK, but from other
institutions across the UK. And I should also add that right now the
aim is with English data extraction, but we will then be looking at
Welsh as well as part of DISCO UK aims.
And I think hopefully-- No, almost it.
So what's next for us? Finalize data collection, do our user
interviews to work out what the interface should look like and what other things
we should be extracting. Hiring, of course, workflow
development, platform development, user testing, and that's it.
And maybe you'll see more about Scribe in future TADWigs.
Thank you.
Thank you very much. We will not take questions, but you can post your questions
on the online application, or also
online participants can post their questions in there as well,
and
hopefully Arita is going to answer in there.
Our next speaker is Greta Pasch.
Good morning. My name is Greta Pasch.
I
spent many intensely happy years managing library and archival
systems and digitization projects, and
then COVID got us, and during COVID, I became a birder,
a really avid birder, and I got so hooked that I
decided to enroll in a master's program at Cornell University, the
home of the Lab of Ornithology.
And as you can probably tell, I was not the average student.
The typical student, I mean.
At the university, I met Vanja Rover.
He's the curator of birds at the Cornell University Museum of Vertebrates,
and I began volunteering in the oology collection.
So this was a new field for me. Oology is the study
and collecting of birds' eggs,
and I was surprised to hear that it was a very popular hobby 100 years
ago.
So I started working with the egg sets and many of these cards
that got me hooked immediately. This is for a Baltimore oriole nest
in Ontario, 1937, and it describes the nest as greyish
hemp and fibers, wool, coarse and fine grasses,
fine strips of bark, and horse hair.
Vanja Rover, he uses these cards to study how nest
materials have changed throughout the years.
So it's very important information, but it's trapped in these cards.
And these cards matter because today, nests have changed a lot.
This is a photo of a Baltimore oriole nest that Vanya photographed.
It's woven with strips of blue plastic, so things have
changed. But the change is only visible against all that
data trapped in those cards. So museums worldwide are
holding maybe two million exits, and many have cards like that
one.
Some digital catalogs may have digitized the metadata, but not the
transcription of the nest.
So that is information that hasn't been transcribed, and that's
both
a research opportunity and a big transcription challenge.
So in 2024,
I was working with a collection from Robert Lyle, who was a collector in
Tennessee.
And I decided to test whether GPT-4o could help.
I photographed 262 cards from that collection
using my iPhone,
and I sent them through GPT-4o.
GPT-4o transcribed the whole card, but I will focus only on
the nest descriptions since that's the rich part of data that we want to work on.
So out of 262 transcripts, 193 were
exact. That's three out of four. And I thought, "Wow, this
is amazing."
The typed cards were nearly perfect, so let's focus only on the
handwritten cards. Two in three of those were
exact. And I thought, "Wow, that's great," but it's also
frustrating because
there's no way I can know which one is correct and which one needs
changes
if I don't open each one and check it.
So my question was very naively, how can the model
tell me
which one is right, which one is wrong?
And I went reading the manual,
and I found this setting, logprops.
I'm just curious, how many of you have used or heard about logprops?
Okay, a couple of you.
The log probabilities is a signal that some models can give you.
If you set logprops equal true like I did here, the model will
report how sure it was of every token that it wrote.
And also, in this case, I'm asking for the five top
alternatives that it considered.
By the way, a token, as probably most of you know, is simply a
word or a part of a word.
So let's look at an example. This is a ring-billed gull card
for a gull colony in Oregon, 1939. Describes the nest
as made of bits of tulle and feathers, and perhaps
2,000 pairs nesting there.
So the model tells us what it almost wrote.
When the model wrote feathers, it was
99.997%
certain.
It didn't hesitate at all.
But for colony, it wrote 7,000 and it was only
58% sure.
So the other option, 2,000, was behind it.
It was the second top one at 27% of
certainty.
So this means that the model hesitated exactly where it went wrong.
That seemed like the perfect signal, so I dug deeper.
First, I decided to call a token hesitant when the
top choice is less than 2.7 times as likely as a runner-up.
7,000 is only 2.1 times as likely, so it's hesitant.
But nesting versus resting was hesitant too and
still correct.
So hesitation may mark uncertainty, but not necessarily
errors, which is what we were after.
So this is every token on the gull card.
Fifty-five tokens are confident and only two are hesitant.
So I defined card hesitation score as the number of hesitant tokens.
So for this card, the card hesitation score is two.
And here you can see all 201 handwritten cards by hesitation
score. Color shows how many words I corrected.
A few cards on the left had no hesitation, but still needed
fixes. The model makes confident errors.
And a very few hesitant cards were still exact.
But look where the dark dots gather, on the right long tail.
Let's look at the furthest one, the darkest dot at 13.
It's for a gray-tailed grackle set, Texas,
1938. Pre-printed dots, no punctuation,
kind of messy writing. Words like stump and inner
lining that are really hard to read.
The card says about 14 feet up, and the model wrote almost 4
feet.
This is a card for an expert reviewer.
So I defined three lanes. A light lane for zero or one
hesitant tokens, a standard lane, two to four, five and up.
Cards like the grackle card, difficult ones for the experts.
Expert lane cards took me much longer, so I measured the time.
My review tool read each transcript aloud while
I followed the card. If it matched, I pressed Enter.
If not, I correct it, and the tool timed my correction time.
Median correction time is under a second in the light and standard
lanes. Eleven seconds in the expert lane.
So hesitation may not signal correctness, but it seems to track
review effort.
And this held very well on 2,303 new
handwritten cards from the Western Foundation of Vertebrate Zoology,
also transcribed by GPT-4o. A different mix of collectors and
hands, harder cards. I used the same three lanes.
Median correction times are stated there.
And so these three lanes and the step-up in the
review time isn't a quirk of one collection.
The lanes still seem to sort the work.
The practical result is that for both collections, the expert lane
contains about a fifth of the cards and takes up half to
two-thirds of the correction time.
So if you
time a sample of your cards, you could estimate how long the
rest will take and see which cards need your most experienced reader
and the most time. Of course, models have moved on
since I started this.
GPT-4o read two in three exactly right.
In my tests with the newer models, Gemini 3.1 Pro,
Opus 5,
those get nearly nine in 10 correctly, but they don't
expose log probs. So does any of this still matter
today?
I think it does, because nine in 10 still doesn't tell you
which one wasn't correct.
Gemini 3.1 Pro and Opus 5 write exactly the same thing for
98.5% of the words.
When these models agree, I found that they are right about
997 times out of 1,000. So still
not always.
Where the ink is ambiguous, both wrote clump for stump,
but you see it's really hard to read, right?
And this is also where GPT-4o hesitated.
Both still modernized the spelling for bulrushes.
There was nothing to do about that.
So agreement helps sort the cards, but it doesn't certify them.
Somebody still has to check, and the job should be to make that
checking easier.
So what did we learn?
First, models already read most of these cards well, but none of them
tells you which ones are right. Second, hesitation
doesn't catch every error, but it predicts the review work.
A fifth of the cards take half the time or more, and you can see which fifth
before you start. Third, the best models don't report their
probabilities, but GPT-4o or any other open-weight model you
run yourself still can.
I will be working on this further.
In my library years, I learned that the key to digitizing
was not the scanning, it was the people describing, checking,
correcting the records, and it's the same here.
The question is not, can I trust the transcript?
It's where should the human effort go?
And two million cards, like that 1937 Oriole card,
are waiting for us. Thank you.
Great timing, Greta. Thank you so much.
Okay.
We will have a couple of questions.
Thank you for that amazing presentation.
Thank you.
What a wonderful method. It was really incredible.
It's too bad that log probs is not exposed anymore.
Have you tried asking the model to rate its own confidence,
and do you have faith in that as a measure of its confidence?
Yeah. At the beginning, I tried that, and it's not something that the model can do
consistently.
Yeah.
Is there any alternative? And do you know if smaller
models are still able to report those probabilities?
For now, Gemini 2.1 Flash, I think still does it, but
that's going to be deprecated soon as well.
That's why I'm thinking about open-weights models.
I haven't played with those, but I'm pretty sure with those, I would have to see
how they work,
to see if they report the same thing.
But Gemini 2, I think it's 2.1,
and GPT-4o match in their hesitation
scores so far. So there's hope.
Thank you.
Yeah.
We can have another question.
Anybody has a question?
Then we will continue with the next speaker-
Okay. Thank you
... Yann Ondoh. Thank you very much, Greta.
Thanks.
Can you hear me okay? Yeah.
So I've got a lot of things to say, but not much time.
So bear with me if I fly over a couple of slides
towards the end.
So my name is Yann Ondoh from UNEP-WCMC,
and today I'll be presenting some work I've been doing on
using large language models to extract biodiversity knowledge
from taxonomic literature. And more specifically,
I will show how to extract that information and
turn it into a structured evidence
knowledge base for species habitat preferences.
So I'm not going to start
by talking about AI, but by talking about the enormous
amount of biodiversity knowledge that has been accumulated over
centuries.
So natural history collections are
product of centuries of explorations and
collections of species specimens.
Observations about species, where they were found,
also
the environment in which they occurred.
A lot of that information
has been compiled into a huge amount of
taxonomic knowledge and has an example
in
Floras, faunas,
checklist, and taxonomic literature.
So there's a huge source of ecological knowledge,
but much of it is embedded into text.
And one useful piece of information in this literature
is taxonomic treatment.
So taxonomic treatment
brings together a lot of information about species.
For example, here is taxonomic treatment for Dalbergia menoides.
Sorry, talking a bit too loud.
And in taxonomic treatments that contain a lot of information
besides taxonomy, we also contain information about the species
distributions
of interest for us, habitat information, but also the
phenology and diagnosis, so comparison with other
species, and also morphological descriptions.
So through Treatment Bank, Plazi has been doing a
tremendous amount of work making
that literature machine accessible.
So now we have over 1.2 million taxonomic treatments
from about almost
94,000 articles.
So it's good to have that literature
digitized
and accessible, but it doesn't mean that the ecological knowledge
that is contained into that literature is
immediately reusable.
So for taxonomy, we have a lot of structured knowledge
systems that already harvest taxonomic treatments.
For species occurrences, we have infrastructure like GBIF.
And if I ask simple questions like what
habitat that these species actually prefer,
there isn't any comprehensive resources I can go
to, to answer that questions. And that question mark is
essentially
the motivation for this work.
So what we propose is to
create a framework that's going to turn habitat information into
structured knowledge base.
And the framework contain four
main components. We start on the left with taxonomic treatment from
Treatment Bank, release our RDF files.
Second, we pass those files into a
knowledge graph that we call a source graph that preserves
informations on the
publications and also on the structure and relationships in the taxonomic
treatments.
Third, we use AI to identify and extract habitat
information from the source text, and we construct an evidence graph.
And finally, we
integrate that evidence with
external environmental and spatial knowledge.
For example, the environmental ontologies, the Terrestrial
Ecoregion of the world, and conservation-oriented
classifications like the one used by the IUCN.
So this graph
structure is really important because it preserves information
about the evidence that we gathered, and we can trace it back to the
original content.
So the next slide is that architecture but
in more detailed way. So we still have on the left the
RDF from Treatment Banks that we transform into resource graphs,
where publications,
treatments, and informations,
and all the information in their sections are still preserved
explicitly. And the evidence
graphs add the information that we extracted
about habitats or geographic evidence,
while retaining the connections back to the original
treatment and publications.
So what you have to retain from
the slides is we're not inventing entirely new
vocabularies.
Wherever possible, we use
existing standards and ontologies.
So the next question is, okay, now we have our graphs,
how we can identify and extract habitat
informations.
So we use an instruction model, here, Qwen
2.5,
but with some prompt principles.
So we
instructed the model to
not infer information from altitude, for example, or
name places, or coordinates, et cetera, and just to focus
on the habitat informations. So it's better if I give a quick
example.
In the first example, so we expect the model to retrieve
that the species occurs in humid evergreen forest on rocky slopes.
That's what it did.
And on the second examples, the model didn't retrieve anything as
expected because it doesn't contain any explicit habitat information.
So
the next question is also, okay, now that we have extracted our
informations,
we would like to know
if we can use that model to
link that to really special knowledge and if the
literature can tell us about environmental regions
explicitly. So for these experiments, we processed over
four
40,000 taxonomic sections that we
extracted
habitat context from.
And separately, we also have
environmental descriptions about
ecoregions that we also extracted information.
And we trained the model, what we call the habitat environmental
compatibility model,
that we call the HECC. So what the HECC?
So HECC is the model is going to learn about the
association between habitats and environmental context and
give it a score of compatibility. So if you have
habitat descriptions and try to match it with environments
which are most compatible with,
that would provide some special support to your
habitat evidence.
So basically, I'm not going to talk too much on this
slide. So basically, the model
is encouraging, but we have some clear limitations.
So we managed to, from ecoregions that were already in the training
dataset, we managed to get the good
ecoregions 75% of the time in the top three
that we retrieved, and 87% of the time in the top
five.
It's less good
for zero shots. So when we've never seen the ecoregions in the
training dataset, the performance drops to 65%.
So if you remember the beljaminoides, so I dug a little bit
into that species. That was a random pick, but I found this a really interesting
case study.
So that species is poorly documented, so it has been assessed as data
deficient by the IUCN. Couldn't find any picture of it in
the wild.
GBIF only have four records,
and the last observation was a century ago.
So we don't know much about the species, but what we know
is that
from the taxonomic treatments, that the habitat is mangrove forest swamps
along rivers, near the sea, in brackish water, in muddy places.
And
what we do is to-- So for references, that's the information about
the regions where we know it occurs, so in Thailand and the Malaysian
Peninsula.
And the model
gave a score within that region to the most compatible ecoregions,
and I overlay that with the observed occurrences that I found
in GBIF, and it fell right
into the highest compatible ecoregions
and other parts where also the compatibility was
higher.
So I'm just going to fly over this. So basically, there's a
huge amount of information out there which is underutilized,
and I hope that the example I gave gives you a glimpse of how
it could be used and can be really informative, especially for biodiversity
assessment, but also for conservation assessment.
I wanted to give special thanks to Rosie and Ben, who helped
on this, and the wider team
that worked on this project. Thank you very much.
Thank you, Ian. Excellent talk. We have time for one
question only.
Yeah. Thanks for this fantastic talk.
A quick question regarding that mapping you do between, as a semantic description
of the habitat in the original source, for example, that herbarium scan you
showed or from the flora to the ecoregion.
As you've seen this query here, this terminology, it's
really natural language. It's not so normed.
In a way, it is, but you have muddy or such words in.
Do you have an intermediate step? You mentioned ENVO, for example.
Where do you do this mapping? So these natural language
description here, are they transformed that you can map them on the ecoregion
categories, or how do you do that?
Sorry, I understand well. So how I train the model to-
How do you do this comparison between the ecoregions or the spatial
information from the databases with the data you obtain directly,
which is sometimes natural language and
more disparate, I would say, not normed.
Do you norm it intermediately to ENVO or Suite or so?
No. So there's quite a complex workflow
for creating the training datasets.
But from the ecoregions, that's part of the
One Earth initiative. So we have a long description, like a one-pager
descriptions on different aspects of the regions.
And on that, I just
extract what's relevant to habitat informations.
So I have
thousands of that database for each ecoregion, and on the
other side, I have the
habitat extraction text from taxonomy treatments.
But also for the ones that I can get
the geographic coordinates, for example, so I can
extract which ecoregion is appropriate in which
lens. So I can really compare
that text to the other text. So the model I have
is the embedding model, so it just try to learn
not only on the name matching, but more on the
semantically ways. So does it really mean--
Because I have the positive, so I know the answer.
So I train it to recognize the type of language which is used to
describe a particular ecoregion.
So it's not only name matching, it's more of the sentence and
what it means. I don't know if I answered your question. Yeah.
Thank you.
I guess you can continue the discussion after the session during
the breaks.
Our next speaker
is Torsten
Dieckow
Is it here?
Is it virtual?
Hello, my name is Thorsten Dieckoh, and I'm excited to be here to talk to you about
the data transcription from insect specimen labels and the
itemization of those data into Darwin Core fields using machine learning.
Currently, at the Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History, we are digitizing
part of our insect collection, and we're focusing on pollinators.
We have about 2.4 million pollinating insects in our collection that are
preserved or mounted on pins, and we have funding in hand
to digitize about 360,000 of the specimens.
We're focusing on bees, beetles, butterflies, and flies,
and we will digitize all specimens and all species in selected
genera to accomplish this goal. We will
share all data or are already currently sharing those
data in the public domain, both the images and the data, of course.
This project started in June of 2025.
We are using a pinned insect digitization conveyor developed
by Pictory, and we have a setup in our museum where we have three
operators feeding the machine, which allows us to digitize up to
1,500 specimens per day.
You have heard a talk earlier in the week by Jessica Bird about this conveyor
project and some of the digital workflows that we have developed.
I have also given a talk about this bigger project at the Spinach meetings
two weeks ago in Cape Town, and at my last slide of this presentation, I have a
link to that presentation slides as well, if you wanted to learn more about this
project in general.
To make sure we're all on the same page, I just wanted to briefly introduce what a
pinned insect actually is. We see here on the top a
specimen that is photographed with its label attached to
the pin, and then the label laid out on the side.
And on the bottom, those images actually are
photos that are coming off the conveyor and are delivered to us by Pictory,
which is a lateral view of the insect, a dorsal view, and then a frontal view.
And on the right-hand side, the lower right-hand side, you can see the labels, how
they are photographed for this particular specimen, and how they are delivered to
us from Pictory.
The current project uses a human transcription, and
we
have been working with an external vendor called Alembo.
This human transcription was the choice of method at the time,
but Jessica and I decided we would also like to explore a little
bit more machine learning and new technologies to get the data off the
labels. So, for example, in the human transcription, there is no interpretation
of the data.
And that means, for example, an abbreviation of CA, which stands for California,
the state of California here in the United States, it would be transcribed as
CA but not interpreted to mean California.
And on the bottom left, you can see a screenshot of our
transcription QC tool called Osprey.
On the left-hand side is a photo of the two
labels associated with a particular specimen, and on the right-hand side, the text
that is fielded into Darwin Core fields.
So Jessica and I started a collaboration with colleagues
from the University of Maryland, both in computer science and entomology.
And this project of extracting data from
digitized labels was an undergraduate capstone project in the fall of
2025. And our goal was to actually not just work on the
extraction of the letters of the words from labels, but go beyond and actually
itemize these into Darwin Core fields.
The digitization projects across the museum, both previously or now with the
conveyor, obviously
generate many photos of labels. And on the left-hand side, the top left, you can
see an example of our boutique photography when we, as researchers, take
photographs of specimens for our own uses,
and that's how they often laid out.
We have a policy in our museum in entomology that whenever a
specimen from our collection is photographed, the labels also have to be
photographed. And on the right-hand side, you can see an example of
photos of labels that are coming off the conveyor that I mentioned before.
Recently, there have been a few publications that focus on
exactly the same idea of extracting the data using
machine learning.
But the two citations that I have on the bottom of my screen, they
are not going beyond that, the text extraction, and putting it into a long
string and not itemizing those data into Darwin Core fields.
So this is one of the goals that we had in our project.
Our tool that we call LaBeLLum has three main steps, and I want to walk you
through for the next few slides about these steps, what actually happens behind the
scenes. So the first step is the label extraction, and you can see on the left-hand
side two sets of labels photographed from two different specimens with three and
six labels attached to them
respectively.
We're using a computer vision model called YOLO to actually extract now
the
individual labels from the
entire photo. And our initial accuracy was about 95% of
that extraction.
So that's very high, and it works very well.
On the right-hand side, the next step is the text transcription, now taking the
letters and the words off those individualized labels and putting them
into a field, meaning that all the
letters and words are
itemized per label. And you can see on the right-hand side
a photo of four labels, and then below you see in
columns the different fields that have the text that is actually
100% matched to what is shown in the label.
We're using a lightweight Gemini model and the
Gemma 312B
machine learning tool behind it.
Our initial accuracy was about 82%, so there's certainly room for
improvement of that step as well.
The next step is now what we call the bucket extraction, and this is
to now get the data, the
words that are taken off the labels into structured Darwin Core
fields. And here we use, again, the Gemini model provided by
Google, and we have a set of Darwin Core fields that
we think are important for the labels in our
entomology collection to do the basic capturing of the
information. And you can here see the same example of the photo of the
labels on the left, and then on the right-hand side, the now Darwin Core
fielding of those
words and letters
into the right categories. And there's only one arrow that is shown here in that
little yellow box on the bottom right, in that the identified by.
So the identifier, the researcher who put a species name on this particular
specimen, which happened to be a holotype, is actually not identified as
such. And this is something to improve, of course.
The prompts that we are using
are shown here in some overview. We obviously give context to the whole
project. We use controlled vocabularies for the country names,
and we use Darwin Core field definitions to tell the
model what information is behind these different
Darwin Core fields. And then at the bottom, an example of just the output
format that we request
to give us from the model.
One way to test the accuracy
of our tool so far was to compare
100 label images versus the 100 records that actually make
these labels. So this is an example that we used from my
own research. Here are the three label photos shown of specimens that I've
collected. We have 100 of those, and on the right-hand side, the top right, you can
see a screenshot of my research database.
And so my research database actually generates these labels, so we know there's an
exact text match
in the labels. However, obviously on the labels, there's no information about
which Darwin Core field the data are actually coming from.
So the first two examples, the graphs on the bottom show the country text
extraction and the verbatim collection date text extraction, and we have very
high accuracy of 99% and 98%. So there's no problem
at this particular point.
The next
two analyses
refer to the genus and the specific epithet that is
found on those labels. And you can see here we have two issues of
28% of
the two are not getting the correct information.
However, we should say that an example is actually shown in those
two labels in the center
and on the right that there is actually no species and genus
name given on the labels. So the
model did the correct thing and just didn't extract any data, didn't come up with
it. So our accuracy is actually much
higher because it would be 62 plus 28% or 65 plus
28% of accuracy of
getting the correct data of the labels.
So that's very satisfactory in this case.
So in the end, we
are ending up with 7% and 10% of error rate for this
particular genus and specific epithet.
One item that we noticed, which we were a little bit surprised, is to get
that the catalog number, our USNMEN unique identifier, is not
correctly
taken into account and transcribed.
We have two examples here. So on the right-hand side, we have an issue of
35%, there's no text extracted, and here's an example of one of those
labels. So here's clearly a unique identifier, USNMEN number,
but the model didn't recognize this as such.
And then on the
6%, we have an error in which the number seven, which is right here,
is recorded or transcribed as a forward slash and not as the number seven.
And I don't know if you can see it on your screen, but the number seven is actually
in both of those labels very poorly printed.
We print these labels in-house, and there must have been something going on at the
time. So here there's obviously space for improvement, and we have
to find ways how to improve the unique identifier, which is obviously very
important for the database, for the
data to have the correct number associated with the data.
So in summary, we need to improve some of our
prompting for the Darwin Core fields and work on some other refinements, and we are
doing that right now. We hope to develop Labellum as
a self-contained tool to run on a laptop and a desktop computer.
And we plan to publish our results and then share with the naturalistic
collection community so other museums, other collections can utilize our
tool for exactly the thousands of
digitized labels being transcribed with the use of Labellum and then
come up with Darwin Core compliant data for import into the database or for
other uses.
At the bottom, the QR code will bring you to the presentation slides on
Figshare, so you can look through my presentation again and explore all the links
that I have in here. And I mentioned in the beginning or further
earlier that my talk at the Spanish meeting and here on the bottom right is
also QR code for exploring the slides and learning more about the
digitization project that Jessica also presented earlier at Tetrick meeting.
Thank you very much for your attention.
Thank you, Torsten.
If we can unmute him, if he is online, he can take questions.
Otherwise, you can submit your questions on the Whova
application. We will continue with the
Pyrian Karunagulatnam.
Good morning. I'm Pyrian, a research associate from Q.
This is joint work with Nikki Nicholson and the APNI team at Q.
I'm going to be talking about a pipeline we've built that uses large language
models for Nomenclature Act extraction into more structured records
for APNI.
First, some context about the International Plant Name Index,
otherwise known as IPNI. So IPNI is the nomenclature index of vascular
plant names published under the ICN, so the International Code of Nomenclature for
algae, fungi, and plants. For each name, it records the
author's type specimen, place, date of publication, and much more
information extracted from these taxonomic publications.
It currently holds over 1.4 million plant names drawn from
18,500 publications by over 55,000
authors. It is curated and maintained by the Plant and
Fungal Names team at Kew.
As an important data source for global taxonomic backbones such as GBIF,
any errors in IPNI would propagate downstream, so the information
needs to be highly accurate.
Now, new treatments are published continuously across hundreds of journals,
and a single paper might describe several new species,
combinations, or status changes.
And getting this information out currently relies on manual curation of very dense
text, which is the big problem. Why? The text is difficult.
It's abbreviation-heavy, it's partly in Latin, and again,
the formatting is inconsistent across journals and publishers.
There is no shared structure to exploit.
Because there's no shared structure to exploit, rule-based parsing doesn't
generalize.
What does this mean? This means the curation is expensive.
So to give you a scale, hundreds of publications are screened every year by
just a handful of editors. It is labor-intensive.
It's slow, mainly because it has to be highly accurate, because errors
propagate downstream into resources like GBIF and POHa.
This combination of unstructured input and a very high accuracy bar is exactly the
problem we can solve using a large language model.
So the solution is a two-stage large language model pipeline that basically
takes in the PDF, converts it into a markdown,
cleans it for any tables or images,
finds where the treatments begin in the anchor detection section, and then we
send those treatments to the
model for a more structured extraction, which is then output as our
CSV and JSON files
used for curator review.
So pre-processing step is simple.
We take the input PDF and convert into markdown using the PyMuPDF Python
library. We then clean out images, image captions, and tables,
because these are kept out
optionally from the anchor and extraction steps, so they don't pollute them.
In parallel, we also retrieve the publication metadata from Crossref,
and with a fallback to default publication details if
no DOI is found. On the next step, we take the
section text, and we send it to the large language models to be scanned for
treatment boundaries. So this will be
basically the taxon name, the nomenclature act, pad with
authors and any additional information such as figure references or table
references and so on and so forth.
The model proposes candidates, which we then ground against
the source document. So basically, we do an exact match first
against lines in the document, and then we fall back to fuzzy matching if it
doesn't match.
And this is done to validate, and this is validated against a similarity
threshold of
90%.
This means an anchor only survives if it corresponds to a real span of text in
the document rather than something the model has reconstructed.
And thus, we have the outputs
treatments to send to the large language model again for extraction, which...
So in this step, each of these treatment blocks is then sent to the model
individually with the detailed extraction prompts.
Sending them one at a time keeps the context small, so no dense treatment
can bleed into the next. The output is also constrained with a finite
schema we've defined with over 30 fields.
The fields grouped into the following: the taxonomy, basin of
information, holotypes and isotype information, collection data,
geographical information, and optionally, descriptions.
And if a response doesn't validate against the schema, we log the failed
extraction, and we carry on. So one bad treatment doesn't just take
down the whole paper.
The post-processing step, we basically take the extract records and merge them with
the publication record. We cross-check
for basic names against IPNI if possible, and we fill it in,
and we then output a JSON/CSV path, with CSV being easier to view
for curators.
As you can see, we have a table of five new noteworthy
species, all from one paper that's been extracted.
Family name is missing because that's not part of the text that was sent to the
model.
And everything else that's relevant has been extracted.
So the pipeline is model-agnostic by design through LangChain.
We support two serving routes, Hugging Face transformers for more local,
smaller models, so you can run on your own device, or vLLM
models,
so you can host larger models like the Qwen 3.8 27 billion parameter
model on an HPC.
We've used the Qwen 3.8 model hosted on GRC
HPC
for our experiments. The initial experiment we did, the early experiments were on
smaller models, like 7 billion parameter instruct models.
And these showed two problems. One, an increased risk of hallucination.
Two, a reduced reliability on long, complex treatment blocks.
So we moved towards more larger vLLM models to improve the
extraction reliability at scale.
So we have a concrete example here of the source text on the left
and the output
extracted information on the right.
As you can see, the
treatment has been correctly identified with the genus and species epithet,
and also author names correctly split into their
respective fields.
The model has also identified the holotype and
isotype information correctly, and so on with the
latitude and longitude, the coordinates, and also the
locality information.
So basically what this says is that one
chunk of dense abbreviated text in will
mean we get an extracted
information of about 30 fields or more.
So this is the same treatment again, but now we're comparing it to the
live IPNI record instead of the source text.
As you can see, the
full name is correctly identified as per the IPNI record
that's already been ingested. The publication information has also
been correctly identified, including holotype information
and also the collector names. Additionally, as you can identify,
excess information that's already not on the IPNI
record has also been extracted, including such as regions,
etymology,
and et cetera.
So in terms of metrics, we've done a preliminary evaluation
over 50 treatments
against the ground truth we've compiled from IPNI records.
So the evaluation was done separately over both anchor detection and then
conditionally on the field extraction of successfully detected treatments.
The anchor detection at 0.79 F1 score is the weakest link, since everything
downstream is conditioned on it. That's where we are focused on in the next
steps.
But conditional on correctly detected treatments, the name fields
are near the ceiling, and the genus and epithet,
we have high precision, high recall for them, and so same with
the other fields as well. This means that the fields
are either being general and over-extracting information, which
means curators just have to reject this information, or it doesn't guess
and extract only the relevant information where needed.
So in terms of limitations, the main factor is the formatting variants across
journals and publishers. Each publisher would have a different type setting that
would contribute to different extraction failures.
This mainly affects anchor detection, as some formats can be different, such
as taxonomic treatments can be referenced in text, it can be part of the
notes section or part of the table of contents.
This would fool the pipeline from identifying which
line is the start of a taxonomic treatment.
Additionally, if publication data is not part of Crossref data, this
is skipped, and we also find some occasional isolation in the structure
extraction, particularly on dense treatments, such as multi author collector
names can be truncated to a first name.
And curator validation, this is not much of a limitation, but more of a
requirement, as this project is not indexed for direct ingestion
without human review, due to the high
degree of the accuracy we need for this task.
So yeah.
Finally, all of this is wrapped in a Gradio interface, so curators can use it
without touching any code. You can drop in a PDF or a whole folder and
choose the model, and download the results as JSON or CSV.
Thank you for listening. This project was made possible using the Global Diversity
HPC cluster, and thanks to Nikki, Helen, and William with all their
help with the project. Happy to take questions now.
Thank you, Pirian.
If
Pirian is online, we can
take some questions.
Pirian, can you say hi?
Is he on mute? Yeah.
Are there any questions? There is one question.
Hi.
That was a very interesting
talk because we are trying to do something
similar. So
do I understand that correctly that you skip
the descriptions and only focus on the other
stuff? Or what are you doing with the descriptions?
So currently,
we've talked about this with the IPNI team as well, and they've
mentioned that the description is currently optional.
That's been updated
in IPNI.
So for the tests we've done so far,
we haven't used them. But the model is capable of extracting the
descriptions at scale.
Okay.
Thank you. Any other question?
We will continue with the next speaker,
Yağmur Güleç.
Hello, everyone. I am Yağmur. I work at
OGSL as a programmer analyst. I develop
AI-powered applications,
especially for extracting information from documents.
And
our
presentation will be on extracting structured biodiversity
knowledge from literature with AI-assisted workflows.
I'd like to introduce and thank my colleagues for their
help and support,
Maria Emilia, Mathilde, and Benjamin.
SLGO is a nonprofit organization
founded in 2005. We work with more than 60
partners from various sectors, such as universities and communities.
And our mission is to provide access to quality open data
on the ecosystems of the St. Lawrence. The St.
Lawrence is a key oceanographic system which largely
supports marine diversity in Quebec, Canada.
Access to this data allows us to meet user needs,
support our collaborators, contribute to decision-making by
governments and communities, and improve understanding of this
system. Since 2019, SLGO has been
one of the three regional associations of the
Canadian Integrated Ocean Observing System, or
known as CIOOS.
A significant share of biodiversity information is found in
gray literature, such as reports, theses,
nonprofit documents, and field notes, rather than in
structured machine-readable form.
Our data catalog also holds a large number of PDF
documents, most of which contain tabular data hidden
inside. This keeps the data out of reach for
analysis and reuse, leaving it poorly
interoperable and difficult to standardize.
And extracting these tables manually is also
highly time-consuming. SLGO prioritizes
to apply
FAIR data principles.
However, the tables inside the PDFs
may not obey the
principles of FAIR data
for some reasons.
For instance, scanned image. If the tables are behind
scanned image,
it prevents them from being found and being searched,
and
the tables inside documents are not accessible
and not retrievable through open standards.
They are
poorly interoperable
since they don't fit in a machine-readable format,
and unfortunately, they
may not be reusable for further analysis
as long as they are trapped inside documents.
To solve this problem, we develop an in-house tool that
extracts table from documents containing both scanned
images and born-digital pages. Born-digital pages
are those with the content typed into a software and
saved straight to the file as a
machine-readable text.
For born-digital pages,
the text layer is enough for table extraction.
However, this is not the case for scanned documents.
For this reason, our pipeline falls back to
an AI-powered solution, more specifically,
modern optical character recognition
with Tesseract engine.
This design avoids running costly OCR
every time
when we don't need.
I'd like to introduce our interface, our in-house
application here.
It starts with uploading a PDF document.
After
uploading the PDF file, you may see
the pages visualize the PDF and navigate through the PDF.
When you scroll down a little bit, you may see the list of table.
Once you clicked on a table, you can visualize
which table is referred
to the chosen table with its bounding box.
And in detail, you may see the preview of the
table to be exported
once you collapse in the menu.
Once you export each table in a different
file in CSV format,
you may
see each table
as a file.
Open one of the file as an example, and you may see
all the data inside this table, and you can
manipulate with an office program like this.
I'd like to show you how we reconstruct the table
from the document
all the way down to a CSV format. For instance, on the
left-hand side,
there is one example table.
On the right-hand side,
how we
reconstruct the table in CSV format.
For instance, every line in CSV format
represent one row.
You can see clearly how merged cells is
represented in CSV format as empty,
so that we know this cell is merged in the
beginning.
The accuracy of our tool with human validation with
19 documents. All the tables were all born
digital.
We use two metrics here, one of which is
precision, the other is recall. Precision is more
trustworthiness of the tool. Recall
shows us
what the tool missed
during the deduction process.
So
our precision 83%
with the 67% recall
is
if we interpret recall
as a
one-third tables missed,
an overall
average
in terms of performance and accuracy,
75%.
Roughly, we can say 75%.
And false positives are the
room for improvement of the precision.
They are indeed
not table. However, the tool
detects them as tables.
For instance,
list of tables and table of contents in documents.
Recall,
for the improvement of recall,
we need to focus on missing tables.
Indeed, we wanted to capture these tables.
However,
the tool
couldn't capture these tables
as a result.
According to our analysis and accuracy measurements,
we see the missing table, the table being missed
by the tool were the problematic ones.
Once we look at some samples from problematic
tables, we see the tables with one column or
the tables with two column were the ones mostly being
missed by the tool.
And also, we need to extend our test strategy with
scanned tables since we didn't have a scanned
table data set.
And also in terms of technique,
maybe hybridizing
with
PaddleOCR
with Tesseract may
improve
the accuracy
and as a plan B,
we may discover vision language models.
As a result of our analysis, we end up with
the tool with 83%
precision and 67% recall.
And the table being missed here is the
main area for improvement. Once we improve
this aspect,
we can
see the high potential for partial automation
directly from
the gray literature
and to our existing data pipeline, where
the raw tabular data is fed
for standardization.
In the end, we will
end up with a more enriched and diversified
standardized biodiversity
data set.
Thanks for listening.
If you have any questions, you may contact from my email address and
Esra Geo's email address.
Follow us on social media
and follow the news from the website and
have a good day.
Thank you, Yağmur.
You can
post your questions in the Huwa application, or you can send her an email
as she said.
So thank you all for the speakers, all of the
speakers. That was a wonderful session.
Try to find each other during the break or
if you want to stay, continue
with the discussion, we can do a little bit more.
I'll be here, but our time is over.
In the second session, there will be two sessions.
In the second session, instead of
knowledge production,
we will be focusing on the already produced knowledge.
How do we curate, how do we do
further research on already produced
data sets? And then, I also want to
tell everyone that in the unconference in the afternoon, we
are having a session specifically on AI readiness concept,
and that will be
if anyone interested in an easy
publication, there will be a publication at the end of that session.
It is not a session,
we will just gathering together with friends
and then trying to
understand how we describe the AI readiness concept.
So, if you are interested, there will be an unconference in the
afternoon. Otherwise, I hope to see you guys
after the break.
Thank you.
No,
no, no. Well, yeah. No, really lovely to meet you.
Drop me an email and yeah, I'm up for collaborating
on films. I love what
you're
doing.
Let's chat.
So yeah, because obviously the D13 is at the-
Oh, sorry. Yeah, I remember I said that.
It was in LA.
It's hard. Definitely tough.
Pretty different for those of us-
Yeah, yeah. No, I know.
You're showing your bias.
No, no.
Well, you've got a new director now or you will have next year.
There was a talk on that actually
about using sort of generating narratives
through
your reference.
That's
been
happening for many years, but to tell a story to make it exciting.
We did it with ship's logs, actually.
So we had these ship's logs, and we basically reunited them with their
collections and managed to mine lots of material from that.
But the storytelling of that, 100% agree.
I'd say getting our public engagement people kind of fully aligned
with that is the challenge. That's why I mentioned Peter and his team, because I
think they have this new
group
focused on finding ways in which archives achieve that science and public
engagement better. And in fact, they are talking about things
like pantry notebooks as a source to do that.
I think their understanding of what that is has got a long way to go.
But that's
interesting.
One of the tools we're looking at for stories is Omeka.
But we also want to make one
specific. And I really don't know what
that is.
There are these sort of storytelling...
They're not storytelling
apps as such, but they are ways of basically extracting
that data within a human curation to tell that story.
Well, so I think we can use the focus group story.
And I don't know whether that-
So
they don't bring up. It's more like the general public.
Which really is what we're talking to.
This tiny-
Well, I don't know about that.
But we have a lot of stories to tell.
We have a lot of resources to draw from.
And I think that's
true.
Well, I think it's either I live too much, so I think there's no
excuse. Well, I guess-
But does it recognize-
A friend anymore.
I mean, internationally,
Montreal isn't that far.
If I'm not there-
Oh, no.
That's okay.
I just-
We get some coffee up here.
And I have a chance to catch my bus.
Oh, have you?
Yeah.
Well, that's-
Well, really nice to meet you. And yeah, just drop me a line.
Give me a ring sometime.
No problem.
Several times over.
Yeah.
That's already happening.
No, it'll be there.
Don't worry.
All right. Great to meet you.
Okay.
We'll do this again
next
year.
Thanks, Mark.
Researchers or general public?
Yeah.
Oh, okay. You probably have a better idea about that because you're trying to
answer questions for people.
Are these loaded questions?
Why are you asking me why?
Yeah.
Because typically, researchers don't get
these.
I don't think we are.
Yeah.
It's like the more narrow your group of people is, usually it's
easier because one person can knock out the parts that the broader group
cannot.
Oh, because
everybody's
got one way of looking at this.
No.
It is what you are.
Well, it depends on the matter after you were involved with it.
There's a couple of people.
At least we both agree.
That's true.
They'll interpret it how they see it.
Yeah.
I don't envy that part. We can specify we're probably bringing up a thousand
worlds.
That's a good point.
People with
questions from
what is a green thing on the ground to
varying that research question to asking what's the size of the particles in the
green portion of the plant.
The default for a group is to say, "We can do that."
Yeah.
That's the safest thing you can say.
You hope, basically-
Yeah.
... to keep it very general.
Keep it really loose and general.
I know your limits. It's reasonable.
I don't think that other AI
interfaces have the same sort of restriction involved.
I'll tell you, Google overviews is happy to let
you have anything you say.
Do you click on the little question?
I try sometimes to click it, but it's not there.
Oh, really? Wow.
But I often have it that way because it's just easier for me to remember the
non-commercial things. Anything here.
That's what I mean. Yeah.
That's what I mean. Yeah. There's kind of concerns me.
Those are kind of this world truthiness.
Maybe it's where-
World truthiness.
Yeah, right?
We're in a world where things are slightly true.
It's probably something somewhere.
We don't know where that came from.
Maybe it's-
We were scrolling.
Yeah. It's true. And then we repeat it, and then yeah.
It's almost like there's no one who can speak to that because it says it on the
internet.
Without any protection to a ergonomic-
It is.
You kind of got to trust.
You really do. You really do.
That's right.
It's kind of, I
understand that.
Yeah, I know.
At least present certain
things.
It's good.
I think maybe we need to do a better job of this,
but I think the difference is by just taking a more technical approach.
Yeah.
It's not about the response. It's really content
driven.
Yeah.
But I'm very curious.
It's virtual.
Yeah, exactly.
Like getting a license.
Yeah, right.
Look at that speed
run.
Am I going first?
No,
you
can go.
Okay.
I went to talk to Ray.
Really?
Yesterday.
Nice. I didn't know that.
I saw like 100,000 rules.
I see a lot of weird stuff.
Yeah.
Okay, great.
Actually, it's important.
It's okay.
Which one?
This one.
Yeah.
But I think you do it.
Is that
pretty good?
Yeah, right?
That's literally it, yeah.
Oh, after all the work.
I don't know how much more I should put down subjectively.
Probably
because they did pretty well.
There you go. I'm going to say B.
Wow.
Thanks so much.
Thank you.
I would specify.
Just say goodbye for now.
Sorry, I
missed it.
Yeah, sure.
Take care.
You know what? I think you have to go
because
I'm going to give him that.
That's the cost.
You
know
what?
You know me.
I'm holding out.
AI machine.
But then we build up even-
Good.
Everyone on the call.
Finish
your time.
Hello,
everyone.
This is the second session of the LLM applications in the
biodiversity data, and in this session, we will focus mainly on
already produced biodiversity
data.
And our first speaker is
Bahadır Altuntas.
Hi, everyone. I'm Bahadır Altuntas, and today I'm going to talk about
automated landmark detection from scalable morphometric data extraction from
digitized fish collections.
So the morphometric is very important
to analyze the biological
shape and sizes for different species.
We do it mostly by annotating
these shapes from the images mostly.
But annotation is very time-consuming, especially if
you have too many landmark and too many points to annotate or too many
areas to annotate. Our goal is here to make the
things easier for landmarking using machine learning.
So we are trying to landmark these
biological images
automatically with a machine learning approach.
So as a dataset,
we have 48 species from genus Nothropis and American minnows,
and we have 28 anatomical
landmarks or morphological landmarks identified from the
literature. And for a training set, we used 217
images, and for testing, we have used 250
images. At the beginning, we
create a training set by the manual
annotation. The manual annotations are done by
using the Stereomorph script. We record the coordinates of
the landmarks of different
images for different species. The important thing here is the
high accuracy. So
from this Stereomorph R script,
we get an XML file for all the landmarks
marked.
And we will use this XML file later for the
training data. So in our pipeline
for the
automatic landmarking, we use the Dlib machine learning library.
Actually, this is
the basic library,
which uses
pattern recognition
in basics. So why we use that? Because it's fast
and lightweight, so in our work for the fast
results. So it's very easy to use.
It has a CPU efficiency.
So
some of the more pretrained models available,
most from the face recognition, if you
see a face recognition
resource or works, probably they use Dlib
library. So you can easily extend this
for the purposes other than the face recognition.
It used regression-based model for
predicting landmark positions, and our input
was 28 landmark for each images for this.
And in our pipeline, first, we
need to
detect the object from the
museum images.
So we have a
model for that also we have produced earlier,
and after that, we crop the images of the
fish,
then
we landmarked it manually and
convert it to the XML format
for using in Dlib
library. So this is for the
manual annotating. So for the landmarks, after this
manual annotation, and if you have an XML file, all
the coordinate, not the XML file, actually.
If you have all the coordinates, you can prepare the
input file for the Dlib library. To use in the
dlib library. Then we trained our
model
for this automated landmark detection.
And our landmark detection workflow is the same
as the annotation
workflow, actually. So we get the original image, we crop,
we detect
the fish images from this museum image, and we
cropped all the images from there.
Then we
try to put landmarks automatically using our
model here. So as you can see in the picture, the landmarks are
produced like this. Put the X
on the image where
the corresponding landmark placed.
So for
our test purposes,
we had the manual annotated images, and we
trained the model. And also we have another
set of images,
250 images, for test
purposes, which is also annotated manually.
So we know the exact positions of the landmarks.
But for our test of our model, we use
this 250 images to get the
automated landmark positions. So we give
these images to our model, and we get
some landmark positions automatically, and we
compare our manual annotations with our
model annotations. So for thresholds,
0.02 threshold, we get
95%. And for 0.01 error
threshold, we get
85.3 accuracy. Of course, we use the
Euclidean distance between predicted and actual
annotations, actual landmark coordinates to get these
accuracy results.
And it's pretty promising, I think,
with the
small data set like this.
So if we check the
accuracy of the landmark positions, the outline
landmarks, so other side landmarks,
were more accurate than the inner sides.
Because some of the inner body landmarks are sometimes not
visible, maybe, or
our landmarking model cannot recognize or
cannot distinguish two different landmarks
sometimes. But landmarking for the eye is
pretty accurate.
Maybe it's because of the shape of the eye.
It has a specific shape, specific
pattern, actually, other than the others.
So it's different from the other side of the fish.
Eye is different, and it has its own shape and
pattern. Maybe that's the reason for the accuracy of the eye.
So for the Notropis chalybaeus, we have 100% accuracy
almost. And for Notropis
buchanani, we have
65.97 accuracy,
and we have seen 34%
variation observed across species.
So we
try to keep
the training sets
in a good
variation. So we
try to cover almost every species with the same
number of
training
images. But in some way, Notropis
chalybaeus has more accuracy than the
other one. So our high-accuracy
landmarks are like this. They look like this.
So you can see all the landmarks are positioned
nicely and accurately. But low-accuracy
examples, you can see most of the low-accuracy
images
have different shapes.
I mean, they
are curved,
or they have a different view
in the picture. So for the left bottom
picture, you can see it's from the top side, and
sometimes it's folded.
And it's also
same species but different picture, different photograph.
The quality of the picture is different.
But this is challenging for us, so we are going to work
on this also. So the inner landmarks are less
visible, as I said before. So our model is
struggling
with the different shapes images.
So we need to work on
this also. So where you can use this automated landmarking,
you can use it for rapid morphometric analysis across the
large datasets. So it's going to support ecological and
evolutionary studies also. Automated species
differentiation based on other features,
mostly. So of course, there are some limitations for our
research, our work. First of all, we
didn't have enough data for training data
datasets. So we need to increase our dataset.
As I said before, it's very time-consuming, so we need to work on
that. The landmarking 28 positions for each image
accurately is not easy. So it's
time-consuming, so we need to take more time
to add new
images, new data For the
better representation of the species.
So the inner landmark predictions are still challenging, but we need
to see that if we increase the data set or
we need to find another way to make them more visible, maybe.
So those are our limitations for our work.
So for the future work, we can use other models.
Actually, we cannot directly use those models or those
approaches for landmarking, because there are mostly
posing models around. So we need to
modify it, or we need to
make it to use in our purpose for landmarking.
We need to find some way to do that. So we cannot get and
directly use
those models for our purpose. So of course, we need to
increase
our data sets here. It will definitely make some
improvements
for our results. So we need to cover more species, maybe.
There are some works in literature
done with the same kind of species. So it's accurate.
So we can see if you use the same species,
same kind of
images,
you
can get better results. But our problem here is the museum
images are very varying, so they are all different.
All the images in our collections
or in our data set, or from the images from the different
museums are in different forms, different
view. So we need to take care of this also.
So, or we need to cover different kind of images.
So we need to include them in our data set.
So deep learning models show strong potential for landmarking, the
automated landmarking. So we have a significant
accuracy. So with the minimal data
set, actually. So it's useful for scaling morphometric
workflows. So you can add this
landmarking to your morphometric workflows, and it's going to be good for
improving that workflow, I think.
So thank you for listening. So this research is supported
by Atilla University and National Science Foundation and
Imageomics projects.
Thank you, Bahadir.
Thank you. That was already over the time.
We will continue with the next speaker.
If you have questions, you can post them online on the
Whova app. Our next speaker is Steen Dupont.
All right.
Perfect. I'm just going to start with something.
This is a live demo, so it's going to ruin everything from the beginning, but
that's the point. The point is actually not to show whether the system works, it's
to talk about how we do it. I'm just going to put two folders in there, go in here,
and I'm going to ask that to ingest that.
And then we're going to jump over to the talk.
Now,
my name is Steen Dupont. This is a project with
Jack Hollist over there from the Natural History Museum.
Those of you who have seen the names Tyr and Odin and Baldr on the
halls' names, this is Kvasir, another Nordic god, god of knowledge,
slaughtered by two dwarves,
milked for all his blood, and mixed with mead to create the mead of
knowledge.
Some of that dropped down on Earth and is why we have poets.
But let's leave that aside.
Right, we can jump this because that's just what I did.
I want to talk about... If we can skip that.
The thing that we're doing. So Jack and I do stuff,
and one of the things we wanted to do is we wanted to explore AI on hardware.
So not using LLMs in the cloud, using an infrastructure that can
run on machines.
We've done three talks, one about cleaning data, one about exploring data, which is
this one, and then one about creating image data from
specimens.
This one specifically is a pet peeve of mine, and
it's something that I've been wanting to do for a long time, but essentially, so
I'm an IT project program manager.
Going to some of these technology forums and looking at the machines that are being
created now that have a huge amount of capacity,
looking at the rise of agents and how that's used, got me thinking about some of
the old projects that I had. Luckily, we got to borrow some
machines. One of them is this one, which I'll be talking about today.
But of course, using that in a museum infrastructure raises other problems.
When you go and tell them that you're going to let the agents loose, they
freak out.
Luckily,
we had our IT department set up a closed network
that Jack could use for his robots and for other things.
For myself, though, everything's run on this laptop, so there is no
need for that. It runs offline and most of my work was done at home anyway.
But the point is, you can use it at work with your own data without it going in and
out or anywhere, and you're using local models.
What is it I wanted to do?
This is from my PhD time. I simply just wanted more visibility of what my
papers contained, and I didn't want to read them.
I wanted to be able to read the abstract, and I wanted to be able to then
investigate the papers across my literature.
I wanted to be able to see what was most cited, when they were cited, which
sections had most literature, pull out information, but also just
navigate that corpus of knowledge.
So I spoke with Codex.
I'm not a programmer, so most of it done with Corpus, and I built an
infrastructure.
This infrastructure works on an agent that orchestrates everything.
It works on Qwen
3.6 as the main model. It uses Dockling as the parsing.
Then it has a number of Python scripts written by Codex for me.
And then it then stores all that in Neo4j and Quadrant as a vector
database. So essentially building a RAG infrastructure for me
And this is more or less how it works, right?
So I've got PDF, we parse it, we build the corpus, we
normalize it. So those are the two Python scripts.
We store all that in our Neo4j and our quadrant vectors.
I can then ask something.
OpenClaw then decides which
to use. It can just pull the data straight from the database, or it can start
building up a query and asking the vector database about that.
And then it comes down here, and then there's a number of other models, so Kokoro
for audio, et cetera.
That's essentially it.
I thought we'd just dive into it and look at it.
I don't know how much time I have left, but that should be fine.
Because the point was to be able
to
explore
data
that I had.
So hopefully it did ingest. You can see there, it's telling me
that it ingested,
and we're not looking at the same-- Just give me a second.
I think I'm looking at a different screen.
Is that not it? Nope, that's not it. Just give me one second.
Interesting.
Now,
how do I get to that?
Okay, so I'm seeing a different screen apparently.
But maybe if we just run the video then. Just give me one second.
Drag it.
Do I have to drag it somewhere?
Windows.
There you go. Hey.
So there
is my Qwaser, right? So this is the program that I designed.
It's not ready. This is just prototyping to talk about
local AI. You can see that it's ingested two papers, which was the ones I
put in. 11 papers skipped. Those were the ones I had in the folder.
It's created 696 chunks of text that it's provided to the
vector database so it can assimilate those, and then I can ask it about this
chunk of text is closely related to these chunks of text.
What I've also asked the system to do is, so we do have
all our papers here.
I have to do this on the screen.
It's really difficult.
So if I click there,
see I've got my papers there. We can go through that.
We can sort, of course, but what's interesting is when we do pick a paper,
what we see is we see the paper and all the references.
Oh, it should've been that one first.
And this is what I wanted to do. I wanted to see the paper, and I want to see
all the sections, and I wanted to see what references were referenced in each
section. Ideally, what I wanted to do was I wanted to
see what kind of paper it was. I had this idea that if I look at a
paper and all the references were the introduction and none in the
conclusion, that was a very different type of paper than a paper that
had very few references in the introduction and a
huge load in the conclusion. Those were two different kinds of papers to me.
And in actual fact, when we look at it and when we then look at this,
this gives me a bit about that. So I could click on,
I don't know.
So this is Affindala. So this is a taxonomy paper.
If I look here, what you'll see is that these papers are spread over time.
So the description of Affindala is based on a literature that spans
time. I could have this picture where all the papers just line
up underneath the paper, and it's all from two years ago, three years ago.
Gives me a sense of where the literature comes from,
timeliness as well. But it allows me to build up that picture.
And I can explore that. So I could go in. I won't do it now.
I can go in and I can click on each of those references to have a look
at whether they're connected. So I could also go and basically say, "Well, where
does this evidence come from? Where is this evidence in that paper?"
And we could jump to that paper. And again, I don't know if this one is
connected to anything else. It's not.
But if we click that, that should open up where that reference paper is referenced
in any of my other corpus papers.
The idea is
that because we have-- Oh, let's just jump to the slides again, actually,
and finish the slides. So that was Qwaser.
You can have a look at it
at any point if you want. Skip the demo.
Yeah. So this is basically just saying that this is not me making it.
This is AI making it. I oversee what Codex and
OpenClaw are doing,
and then validate through that. So it's very much a prototype.
But these
are sort of the questions around why local AI. So one is security, right?
One is
local models are becoming better. We can see that.
If we optimize them, if we have the first step so that the LLM is not
working on the full body of
processes, but just does the important bit.
We parse it for it, we put it in the database, it does all that.
It becomes a lot easier. And again, just coming back to the
GB10, which we talked about the other way, which is a beefier machine.
It allows researchers to use that as an edge infrastructure.
So instead of having
what is a 7,000-pound machine each, it could be running a normal
institutional laptop and running this
on an edge compute still within the museum, but you can run
10 or 20 users at a time on that machine.
So it becomes an AI infrastructure where you can prototype, you can use, you can
play, you can build before you decide to deploy it, or just for
yourself, for that matter.
I think that's more or less it. Let's just have a look. Let's thank you.
I wanted to say one thing
just before we finish. One of the ideas was to play around with agents.
The agent in this setup doesn't actually do that much It
decides my question and where to
push and where to pull the data from.
But anything I want to add onto this, the agent becomes the orchestration layer.
So if I want to add a separate-- This is all run in Dockers.
If I want to add another Docker with an image
vision model, it can decide that when I ask for visions, it'll
reroute to that local model or the other one.
So the agent sits on top as the orchestrator to plug things in,
and that's rather interesting because I don't have to redo the whole
infrastructure. I can just add onto it.
Thank you very much. I hope that was interesting.
Thank you, Steve.
We can have a couple of questions.
Any questions?
Thank you.
Cool.
Oh, there is one question.
Oh, I have to stay here.
So I'm curious when you find those publications and their relationships to each
other, are you then envisioning ways to pull that information
out and into
the database?
Yeah. So I would add that as an extra-- We've seen a lot from other
talks here that are pulling data tables and other things.
You, I would expect, would do the same, right?
So the agent would then allow me to pull that out.
Well, the LLM already does it. You can pull things out in a tabular form or other
things, but there's a lot of validation that still needs to happen-
Sure
... before this works. But yes, you should be able to do that.
So are you--
I guess I'm interested in the UI/UX for what that would look like.
That when somebody says yes.
Well, it has to be one button, because if not, it doesn't work.
Great. All right. Thank you.
Thank you, Steve. We will continue with the next speaker, Roderic
Page.
Can you hear me?
Cool.
So this is one of those talks where the deadline for TED Week seemed so far away,
I thought, "Not a problem. I have something awesome ready to show you." Of course,
I've failed. So this is a rehash of something I've
done before. My new deadline is November for the DNA barcoding meeting
in Bangkok. So if you go to that, hopefully, I have something to show you.
So
about 10 years ago, I published this little dinky little diagram showing a
knowledge graph, and the argument was: Wouldn't it be cool if everything was
connected to everything else? Very obvious kind of thing to do.
I think we'd all think that's a good thing to do.
I've seen it used a few times, which is kind of flattering, but also it makes me
cringe just a little bit, because in the back of my head, I
have this.
If you've ever seen the TV show "Silicon Valley," which actually dates also from 10
years ago, there's a scene in that where this guy, Action Jack Barker, who's
modeled, I guess, on Steve Ballmer, is confronted by a fairly dubious-looking
character, and he basically says, "Before you kind of wave your hands and give me
some b******t,
I want to know what concrete information you can give me that I do not already
possess."
And this is the question I keep asking about knowledge graphs.
They're way cool, but what do they actually give us?
So
I came across this paper a couple of years ago.
This is a really cool paper and archive that gave me some hope that maybe we can
get something. It talked about something called Qurate GPT,
and its argument was that one of the potentially great uses of knowledge graphs
is curation, helping improve data quality.
You take a knowledge graph, you take a chatbot, you put them together, we can
maybe help fix data.
So I've been exploring that in the context of DNA barcoding data.
Now, why barcoding data? Apart from the fact that it's kind of cool and there's
lots of it,
there's lots of problems with barcoding data.
There's about, I don't know, I've lost track, 25 million barcodes in the Bold
database. It's widely used. This is one of the more famous subsets.
This is five million barcodes used to train models to
identify things. The vast majority of these insects, we do not know what they
are to species level. They're identified to order or family.
So we're training these models on basically our ignorance of what these things
are, and I find that slightly disconcerting.
So I built
a little website called Bold View.
I got really fed up with the DNA barcode portal. I don't know what you think of it.
Drives me crazy.
And it's a very simple, kind of crude website, but what I've done is I've used
it to explore the barcode data, and every time I find something that seems a bit
odd, I make a note to myself. "This thing seems to be in the wrong place.
It hasn't got coordinates. It hasn't got a name."
And at some point, I want to figure out, what do we do with that list of things
where these barcodes have clearly got a problem?
So to give you some examples,
this is a little crustacean that lives in temperate mountains,
and according to Bold, it really loves hanging out in the middle of the Australian
desert.
Now, Bold at least is honest. It says the coordinates come from the center of
Australia, but we actually know where this thing is. It's endemic to Tasmania.
So if you're interested in climate,
phylogeography, ecology, you're going to be screwed with that data.
So why have we got that?
Here's another one. This is what Bold knows on the left about this record.
It says it's a caudate, which is fairly
imprecise.
It has a GenBank record. You go to GenBank, and GenBank says this is a snake
from China. So why is Bold being really coy about
what this thing is?
Let me give you a slightly more detailed example.
This is a record in Bold. There's the code there.
It is identified as this, this on CVB03.
That's obviously not a proper species name.
And what we get from Bold is that name, and we get this.
This is a GenBank record. So how do we figure out what that is?
Well, if you go to GenBank, if you're lucky, you'll find a publication record.
Here's a DOI. And if you go and read the paper,
you find that same GenBank record attached to the holotype
of this thing. So this
is that. So it kind of closed the loop.
So this is one of these informal names that actually we do know exactly
what that is. So that's what I want to do.
I want to sort of fix the coordinates and fix those names.
Now, I want to point out that this may sound like data cleaning, and I think it's
more than that.
A lot of data cleaning involves looking at the data and saying, "Is it internally
consistent? Have you got lots of different names for the same barcode bin?"
That flags a problem, but doesn't fix it.
We may map
taxonomic names, say, in BOLD to external databases, and that sort of cleans up the
spelling, but that doesn't fix it. So I think we need more than that.
We need to go externally and find other sources of information that can
help. So I'm interested in how you do that.
One obvious approach is to go to the literature.
This is a paper that described that species, and in that
paper is
a description there. This is the material.
There's the magic number, the holotype, and the GenBank record.
Also, there's images and all sorts of stuff stuck in supplementary material and
tables.
That's what I want. Now, I thought the obvious solution to this is Plazi.
Sadly, no. So Plazi, as probably many of you know, extracts
information from the literature more or less automatically.
I ran this record through Plazi. Plazi is really good at getting latitude and
longitude. It's great for putting dots on maps, loads of data in GBIF.
It does not do well for finding out these things, which is what I need.
I need these kind of codes in that record.
So this is the stumbling block for me at the moment, is to try and extract that
information reliably from the literature.
I have messed about with some LLMs.
This is a very simple prompt in ChatGPT.
It sort of gets most of the stuff. We've seen way more sophisticated
techniques in the last few days, so this is what I really want, is to be able to do
that automatically.
The other thing I need, of course, is I need to link the barcodes to the
literature, which is somewhat tedious.
I've published a dataset linking barcode datasets to the literature.
It's about 1,500 citations. That's a good source.
If you go to GenBank, there's potentially millions of these records, but many of
them are not linked to papers. I need to figure out that.
I'd also want to filter by which of these papers are about taxonomy.
Ideally, which of these ones describe a new species, ideally from the barcodes,
they're potentially going to be useful.
So this is the hard work to get to that point.
So I guess what I'm saying is
if we can flesh out this part of the knowledge graph,
connecting specimens, literature, and sequences, then maybe we can have a good
go at trying to clean up some of the issues with BOLD.
And maybe I can finally get this guy to shut up and actually show him
something concrete and useful.
I have one more thing to show you.
So
this is the kind of toy knowledge graph.
I think this thing is actually starting to happen.
There's some really extraordinary work being done by people in Germany,
Switzerland, and the Netherlands.
The same people have got Wikidata into a Spark or Triplestore.
They've got OpenStreetMap, and they've got GBIF.
Eighty-six billion triples are now available.
And the same project has now got BHL. It's got Binomia.
There's a whole bunch of stuff happening.
So maybe, just maybe, that little cartoon graph will actually become
real. Thanks for your time.
Thank you, Rhodri.
We can have a couple of questions.
I have a question with the
NCBI and GenBank. How easy is it
to
download and find everything you want?
Would you call it AI-ready already, or
did you come across--
It was the same system forever,
and they never
updated, or they did nothing, and we are developing our tools
accordingly. But is there a need for that?
Yeah. The GenBank side of things are slow and tedious.
It would be nice if I could grab specific chunks of it and work with it.
These are all calls
downloading individual records. It's very slow and very tedious.
And then there's the cleaning and the post-processing.
So it's, yes, not straightforward.
Is there any question?
Thank you. Your work always has been inspiring, and it's helping us to think.
I am still struggling with this
sort of edit and annotation or all of these extra things.
To me, it seems like it's always outside the infrastructure.
In a way, it's decentralized, which helps, so you can have it
independently. So let's say if the infrastructure goes away, you can
still have it.
But depending on where the user's coming from, they're not going to see that.
So I'm still struggling to how do you see-- So, for example, all of the
corrections and things,
they're not going to be in BOLD soon.
So the primary user of BOLD probably coming to BOLD
and still seeing the-
Yeah
... the old data, not the correction. So, yeah, I'm just curious.
That's a big challenge. I guess maybe the role model here is something like David
Shorthouse's Binomia, where you've got annotations set up, and then the
question is, how do you get those into GBIF or something?
And I think actually maybe this knowledge graph thing might help because then you
can just see any annotations straight there. But yes, that is the big thing.
Where does all that work go?
We can take one more question.
Did I really talk that fast? Wow.
Very fast. Thank you so much, Frederick.
Michael, right? We will continue with the next speaker,
Michael Elliott.
Hello, everybody. I am Michael Elliott from the University of Florida, the Advanced
Computing Information Systems Lab,
and I'm going to be presenting on iChat Bio.
There it goes. All right. iChat Bio is a project we started in
2024. We first showed it at Tadwig actually a couple years
ago, and it's an agentic AI system for exploring and
interacting with biodiversity data.
You can see it on the right side. It's a web app.
You can interact with it just like you would ChatGPT or any other
chatbot, except it is a multi-agent system, so it's a little bit more
specialized to do biodiversity data related
tasks.
We officially made it public in February of 2025.
We put it at ichatbio.org, like you can see right there.
And as of May 2026, we've had over 2,600
user conversations.
We've developed 14 specialized agents, which I'll explain on the
next slide, and it accesses 11 different data sources.
And in the development of this project, we've been assisted by a total of 12
students. I think I'm involved in that number, or included, so
. Okay. Yeah. So it's a multi-agent system.
When you're sending a request to it, like a question or an instruction,
you're actually sending that to what we call the chat agent.
So this is the agent that interprets your requests and turns them
into sub-tasks that it then delegates to specialized agents,
which you can see on the right side.
So real quick, that QR code on the bottom.
I'm not actually using this mic, I forgot.
The QR code on the bottom there, we have a Python package that we call
the iChat Bio Software Development Kit.
So if you scan that, you can actually see the code that we use to develop agents
and potentially contribute if you'd like.
But on the right side, we can see the list of agents that are currently connected
to iChat Bio. It includes an agent for GBIF, IDIC
Bio, iNaturalist, ALA, OBIS. So that's where our
occurrence records come from. We also have taxonomy from Worms,
literature from BHL, even some climate data from NASA.
And then we have
a grab bag of things. We have some genetic data from NCBI.
We have internet web search powered by Google, and then we
have GloBE for global biotic interactions.
And then there's also a handful of agents that just help the system
function and process data. Also, some visualization capabilities
like generating maps.
Now, what we envision for iChat Bio is to
execute data access, processing, and inference
workflows.
So access, so on the left side, we have data retrieval here.
That typically looks like going to an online API like
GBIF or essentially the machine
accessible version of the search forums that you use through a web browser.
That might be through GBIF or IDBI or any of the others.
Eventually, we'll allow it to download datasets, so if your data are not
indexed, we might be able to still work with it.
And we do currently support user uploads, so you can upload your
TSV or CSV, though it works best with JSON
currently.
Once you have data, you might want to process it a little bit, or the AI might need
to process it to help answer questions.
So that might look like filtering or enrichment of records.
It might look like computing statistics or generating visualizations like
maps or graphs, though we don't support graphs yet.
And it might also involve, for example, taking the data you have and
turning it into a fair data package that you can go do something else
with outside of iChat Bio.
Once you have data processed, then we would want to maybe do some AI inference.
That could just be general question answering.
So how did the data relate to my question?
It could also be data cleaning that requires some measure of intelligence,
kind of ad hoc, see what's in the data, see what's wrong, and try to filter
out the problems.
Or it might look like generating hypotheses.
And if I wasn't clear, I put a star next to the could,
because this is kind of the vision. Not all of this is supported right now.
But we have bits and pieces of all of these three sections.
So, getting onto some examples about how it actually works.
Here, I'm going to show a question that involves two different data sources,
and this is going to be a little bit animated, so sorry if you're trying to take
pictures.
Maybe be quick about it.
So the question I asked was, do any predators of Synclus synclus
have recorded occurrences in Norway?
So if you want to answer this question, where do you start?
One data portal isn't necessarily going to be able to answer this for you.
The iChat Bio chat agent begins by acknowledging my request.
"I understand you would like to know if any predators of this species have
occurrences in Norway. To answer this, I'll first identify predators,
and then I'll check for occurrence records."
It starts by searching global biotic interactions,
and then it sees it created something. We call these artifacts.
This is the data returned from global biotic
interactions.
And if I click on that black box where it said search in GloBE, it'll tell me
exactly how it got the data. So this is all AI generated.
It's using search parameters, submitting a search request to then downloading the
results, and it says it found 75 interactions.
Now, the AI knows that the API results are potentially a little
bit raw, so it wants to process them into just a list of predators.
So it does that, and if we compare the
API results on the left to the list that iChat
Bio generated, we can see it's taken this raw representation to something much
more concise that is just a list of the species names.
Now, getting rid of that, if we continue, it's going
to actually search for records of those species in that list,
and it's going to create a bunch of information that it downloads from GBIF
about the different species. And it is only doing a subset of them.
Because it is a chatbot, it's sort of naturally trained to keep its
responses from getting too long. So it only decided to
look at about 10 of them.
And then that last one, so we do have some bugs occasionally.
You can see the last artifact is described as, "I encountered an
error while trying to generate a description." So
these things are a work in progress, but that last one contains the GBIF
response about these species.
So it says, "Based on the known predators,
I found Vulpes vulpes, Martes, Canis lupus, Ursus,"
et cetera.
But it hasn't actually given me any information about
how many records it found or anything yet.
But first, if you like the response, you can go ahead and hit that
thumbs up. If you did not like it, you can hit the thumbs down and maybe explain
why. But feedback is great, it helps us a lot.
But moving on, I
want to count for each of these predator species that's in GBIF.
So iChat Bio goes to GBIF, looks for more statistics for these species,
and just like with GLOBE, you could go and look and see exactly how it got this
information, and then it generates a list.
So Betel, 151,000 records, et cetera, down the
list.
Another example.
Now, a direction that we're kind of moving toward is trying to have
users be able to define and repeat their own data workflows in iChat
Bio, especially for the kind of workflows that you don't have time or don't
have any kind of existing information,
system, or interface to actually execute these things.
And this is going to be a summary of what I showed in Spinach, so you may have seen
this before, but I ask it, "Retrieve all the specimen records for this fish
species.
For five images of this species, I want you to generate descriptions of the
images and create a table, and then categorize the images."
So I'm essentially trying to extract information from the images in this
data contained in GBIF. And you can see the table here.
I'm not going to go into it too precisely, but
we can see five images that it found.
Three of them are clearly sort of clustered. They're bone preparation sets.
And then there's a
handwritten journal, and then there's a specimen image.
The chat bot created descriptions for all of these. I've reviewed them.
I think they're accurate.
But then it also assigned categories, and they all seem to make sense.
Three are skeletal preparations, one's a catalog or archival document, and the
last is a preserved specimen.
Now,
there's an endless possibility of questions you could ask,
but a couple more examples that might inspire you that you might go ahead and try
at home is, for example, what is the range of air temperatures that
this species has been observed at?
Because we do connect to NASA climate data, so you can take occurrence
records and map climate factors to them, and it
produces a range that's drawn from data, and then you can ask more questions about
that. So, for example, show the occurrence records on a map colored by
climate parameters.
So final take... Go.
Come on, you.
Okay. Thank you. Final takeaways.
Although chat responses can hallucinate because the chat agent is based on
large language models, the responses you see are the outputs of something like
ChatGPT. It can contain mistakes, but the important thing is that
any data that you encounter in iChat Bio are derived from
real data and computed by reliable transformations.
So the data that you see, I will call them traceable, repeatable, and
authentic,
although they might not be exactly what you wanted, but they will be real data.
Nothing will be hallucinated in there.
Point two, iChat Bio connects to data sources through specialized agents, and
anyone can create new agents using the iChat Bio SDK,
or potentially help us develop these agents because they are mostly open source.
Point three, more agents means more synergy, means more
emergent use cases, meaning
you may be able to answer questions that they weren't necessarily designed for by
having a collaboration of agents.
And finally, we're always seeking feedback and collaborations.
So feel free to contact us if you want to see the system get better, or if you
just want to say what it did for you, or what it could do better.
So thank you very much.
Thank you, Michael.
One very quick question.
So in my opinion, GBIF kind of data repositories
are lacking a lot of
terms that we
want to use. Metadata richness is very low, and
then the metadata completeness is-
Actually turn that unrestricted information into structured field
data.
So that's a kind of example where it could help.
But also,
if you have the same occurrence record, for example, showing up in multiple
databases, like maybe it's in GenBank, and GenBank has some information in its
little record of the collection. You might be able to take that, bring it back into
the occurrence record.
Right now, if you wanted to do something like that in iChat Bio, you'd really have
to hold its hand and take it one step at a time just because it
doesn't have reliable mechanisms for long-term,
complex processes.
Okay. Thank you.
Yeah.
Is there any other question?
Thank you for this interesting talk.
My question would relate to you showed that taxonomy
is only coming from worms. Are you planning to extend this to
freshwater or terrestrial environments as well, or to-
Right
... Checklist bang, Catalogue of Life, things like this?
Right. Yeah. Worms is the one that we included there just because it
is our best quality agent currently for taxonomy.
The other taxonomy agents are still a little bit work in progress.
So for example, we're working with Catalogue of Life,
and I think we're doing Plants of the World Online and some other things.
Also, with the web agent, this is sort of a
catchall agent. A lot of the taxonomy information on the
internet is indexed by Google. So for example,
I don't know, flora is something you'll find online, and if you do a Google search
for those, iTrip Bio can potentially find those and pull that information from
there. Because it's a lot different from occurrence records where you don't
necessarily need to interact with a database.
But yeah, we're working on it.
Thank you, Michael.
Thank you.
We will continue with our next speaker, Andrew Tokmakoff.
Hello. My name's Andrew Tokmakoff, and I'm the technical lead at TERN
Ecosystem Surveillance. And I'm presenting this paper, "Reliable
LLM-Assisted Curation of Ecological Survey Data," on behalf of the team,
so Carly, Hoy, Donna, Valeed, and Ben.
So just a bit of context so you understand who we are and what we're doing.
TERN is a government-funded research
infrastructure initiative in Australia for ecological information.
And the
TERN Ecosystem Surveillance team is based in Adelaide, and we've been
established
quite some time, 2011.
Our team has a bunch of ecologists and technical people, and
we have some
field teams that go out in the bush and they collect samples, and I'll go over that
soon.
And they also collect the field data.
And so today we're going to talk about not so much the collection aspects, but
the curation aspects of the data that they collect, which then obviously goes on to
get published.
So this is a small overview of our plots.
So there are many hundreds of them, and many of them get revisited.
The
data we collected is soils and vegetation data.
We also collect samples,
and we collect according to a well-defined protocol, which
has been taken as a basis, and it's actually
been evolved a little bit towards EMSA, which I'll get into in a moment as well.
You can see here also that some of the plots are located in
transects, which allows us to
determine change over time, assuming that there is some.
So further context,
we've been collecting for over a decade with our previous system, which
was AusScribe, which is an Android app, and also
with a CouchDB staging database, Postgres for
persistence, and a simple curation user interface.
We've now gone ahead and built a new system,
which is
based on EMSA standards, and that's a PWA, and it's a schema-driven
system where the front end is driven by the data design that
sits in the back end.
And we've now transitioned to using that new system, but of course, we've got our
old system, which is where our publishing goes.
So we need a bridge to bring the new data in to sit with the old data.
And part of that is a curation mechanism, which is what I'm going to talk a bit
further about today.
So what's the actual problem? The problem is that there's a lot of data, and it's
not possible for any person to really have it 100% clean.
I guess anyone who's managed a decent amount of data would know that.
So the people do
the best they can, but stuff
slips through.
So
what we have found also is that some people
spend a bit more time and energy when they collect and enter their data than
others, so there's different quality there.
Protocols can change over time.
Our ideal path is that our app collects the data and applies a whole bunch of
rules there for completeness and correctness.
And then
when the data gets to our back end,
it has the correct stuff. But we also sideload data
sometimes,
because externals need to use the system, but they haven't been
using the app. So then we actually sideload from Excel, and then you end up
losing all of the
resilience and the rules that you've baked into your field app for
keeping things nice and neat and tidy.
Also, we export the data at the end of the day once it's been
curated and publish it so that it's findable, and that's where we do that in
EcoPlot.
So
the data might
be fine according to the schema, but it's unrealistic.
You can see here there was a 999-meter
hummock grass, which is obviously bogus, and I guess that was a placeholder.
Someone entered that in there saying they'll come back a bit later and fix it, but
they never did.
So it's implausible, but in principle, it's
allowed.
So this is what curators find, but it's very rare.
These things are not systemic data errors.
They're more like
human factors that have happened along the way.
And like I mentioned before,
the validation that lives in the app doesn't actually necessarily move with it, so
we can end up with bad labels that come in through the sideloading.
Declarative and
run against the data, and then the model itself has a
bunch of phases where it can look for certain things as well.
If any findings happen, they go into the findings table
And there's a review dashboard that the curator can see the findings, and
if the curator thinks that the findings are reasonable, then it can say, "Yes, I
approve," and then the findings and the fix are applied, and
then they
are affected in the swarm database.
You'll note also that the model never gets a chance to write
anything directly. It always goes through a human click.
So these rules, what do they look like? They are declarative.
So we can define them in YAML,
and then
that gets converted into a
SQL query that can get run against the database.
And this query should find any, for example,
any plots or any point intercepts where
it's greater than 80 meters. This is something that we would not expect, so this is
an outlier if it finds one. And this is just pure SQL, and we've created
these
rules
through the use of the LLM.
The phases that the model does, and this is an example, one about a species
diversity brief. Basically, we prompt it.
So you can see here for each visit, go through and find these items, and if
a single species is recorded across 50 or more intercepts, this is
not reasonable, so you should flag it.
And don't reason yourself out of it to do with the bioregion, because
we've had it where it did that before.
In one case,
the model dismissed one species across 76 intercepts, and it said, "Oh, well, that
would be normal because it's an arid bioregion." And we think that it's
more like a vouchering issue or a data issue, not a genuine
one species,
100 meter by 100 meter plot.
So
these are the kinds of queries that the
model does,
and this is what it looks like. So you've got the harness, which has got a brief,
which is essentially that prompt that I showed you, and a bunch of tools that are
available to the model. And we send that off to the model, who then
says, "Okay, I'm going to do a query." So it sends back the tool
request to the harness. The harness then does the query on the database, gives
back the rows,
and then it gives that tool result as JSON back to the model, and the model then
has a look at that JSON
and analyze it because it's a smart model.
And then it reports its findings and it says, "Hey, I found these things that don't
look correct."
And then they go into the findings table, and that's then presented to the
curator who can decide whether it's a realistic problem or not.
These are the kinds of classes that we've identified.
So you've got things like
a hummock grass at 999 meters, or a growth form that
doesn't fit with the canopy, or an epiphyte which should
have a host is sitting on bare ground, or a visit that never got closed off, or
two soil horizons that have been inverted, or
a site where you've got more transacts than you would expect.
You should only have 10, but this one would have 13, so there's some sort of data
issue there.
Malformed labels, that came up before because this has been side-loaded.
The app would not allow it, but somehow it got in.
Symbols versus full strings getting in,
and also rules that fire too often that are simply incorrect.
So what we've got here is a snapshot of the review
dashboard.
You can see
the tools on the left-hand side, and you can see the types
of
items that are brought up in the findings user interface.
Also a costing there, the tokens used, and whether it's a full scan or not, et
cetera.
And then here, this is also another example of some findings
where the lats and longs are not correct, and it's suggesting just to null them
out, which I would suggest is probably not the right answer either.
So there's potentially a bit of work to be done there on getting the fixes correct.
But you get the idea that the error is found, and you've got an approve it or don't
approve it button.
Every write to the database passes through the curator, which is a person.
There's not that many of them, so it's a very small number of records for the whole
platform. But
that's where it finds its value, I guess, that it finds these needles in a
haystack.
The adjudication happens by class, not by specific row.
So it's not if it finds 500 of the same thing, you have to
say whether that's reasonable or not. You can say, "Yes, this class is correct.
You've got it right on these," and then it should be in a position to do something
about them.
There's also a query, like a free text query mechanism.
You can simply ask the agent.
So getting the harness right was where all the hard work was.
We had to iterate on it a lot.
What was really important was to make sure that we didn't accept silence as coming
back. So sometimes we would send a query, and we would get nothing back, and we
thought, "Okay, it must be that it has nothing to say," but actually,
it may have failed with a token limit or
just couldn't deal with the question that we're asking it.
So there was a lot of iteration in there,
to make sure that we get genuine
results.
What we found is that there are genuine defects in it,
and there are also some that were false positives.
So a 65-meter tree in a tall wet forest is actually fine.
That's not a problem at all.
And also,
as I mentioned before about using classes, so at one point, one of the
reports was that there were 62 plots with missing
point intercepts, and it turns out that a number of, well, 39 of them were
forest sites, which do not have point intercepts anyway.
So it correctly found that,
but we had to then say, "No, forest sites you don't need to worry about," and
therefore, the rule was adjusted to exclude forests.
So you just keep iterating over these proposals, and some of them are correct, some
of them are not, some of them are too loose, and you can just keep going
until you get some nice tight rules, which then get codified and turned
into those
rules that I showed you before, which is in the YAML that turns into SQL.
You can probably apply this anyway for yourself if you like.
Start with your real curation problems, build your harness,
let the model roam through your data and it will find things. It'll propose them.
You can say yes or no. They will then get turned into rules, and
then the model has less to do because you actually
surface rules and they become things that the model doesn't have to check
anymore.
So you move towards a space where coverage is done.
So yeah, quick takeaway since I'm nearly out of time.
The deterministic rules run first, and these are the ones that surface that the
model finds, and we can tune them and then turn them into
deterministic rules.
Curator is always making sure something is going in or out.
Don't allow it to be quiet, otherwise, that typically means you've got a coding
problem.
Make sure you adjudicate by classes, not by row, and your
tests work if your code works, and evals with a known data set and a known
set of results allow you to evaluate whether your tool is effective or
not, and that's really important as well.
And that's it. So, thanks a lot and yeah, goodbye.
Thank you, Andrew.
We will take one question. Andrew is online.
So I have one question. Andrew,
can you say hi?
Can you unmute?
Hello?
Yeah.
Hello.
Oh, hey. So how do you understand
which curational
tasks require
expert review and which others are safe?
Well, our curator is responsible for the outcomes,
and essentially the system surfaces these rules.
I showed one example there, it was actually wrong.
The rule was okay, but
it had to be tuned. So essentially, all the rules that come up are fine, and
we have our curator who then applies their domain knowledge to
work out whether there's something there or not.
And if there is something, maybe it needs to be tuned a bit.
Okay. Thank you so much, Andrew.
We will continue with the next speaker,
Roseline Gabut.
Hello, everyone. I'm Roseline Gabut from the Department of Computer Science,
University of the Philippines Diliman.
So the amount of biodiversity literature and database records that require
geo-referencing is growing rapidly.
Because of this scale, manual curation alone is no longer enough to keep
up with the task. For example, the Manchester Museum
and Philippine Biodiversity Collections contain hundreds of thousands of
specimen records with geo-referencing still
largely performed manually.
Location is one of the most important pieces of information
in biodiversity occurrence data.
However, many biodiversity databases record
locations only as place names or text descriptions
without geographic coordinates or even hierarchical locality
data. For example, in these three site
records,
are textual descriptions of a collection site.
In the museum's database, there is Valley Africa for the
continent field. However, the rest of the location
hierarchy fields are empty. With these examples, filtering by
country, province, or township is not possible.
Additionally, ambiguity is common in biodiversity
records because of outdated place names, inconsistent
spellings or transcription errors, and overlapping
administrative names across provinces and towns.
This is the geo-referencing pipeline we helped develop.
The pipeline takes as input a CSV file containing
collection site records extracted from EMu.
Site descriptions, which are often provided in narrative form,
are preprocessed using an LLM with geo-names and
Wikidata serving as knowledge bases.
We then apply our geo-referencing method, which uses
Wikidata
to identify the most appropriate geographic entity and
determine the corresponding latitude and longitude
values for each site record. In addition, we developed a
human-in-the-loop tool that allows human annotators to
review and correct the values suggested by the pipeline.
Once validated, the processed data can be downloaded in a
format that can be imported back into EMu.
The dataset consists of collection site records from the African
continent. The locality field is relatively sparse, with
many missing values. In many records, locality
information is instead embedded
within the site name field as narrative descriptions,
such as in this example.
We developed a preprocessing methodology that automatically
populates missing locality fields using information
extracted from the site description.
The workflow, the preprocessing workflow, processes site
records from a CSV file and automatically populates
missing locality fields. It first cleans
and extracts location information,
then uses an LLM to interpret the complete site description and
populate the locality hierarchy.
For fields that remain empty, a per entity fallback uses
spelling correction,
geo names, Wikidata, and the LLM to identify
possible values. Finally, hierarchy enrichment
fills gaps and verifies geographic consistency
before producing the processed CSV with confidence
ratings.
For example, this site record contains values only for
the continent field and the sit site name,
which provides the site description.
Our preprocessing method uses this information to infer
and populate the missing locality fields with the
suggested values shown in this last column,
such as this.
After the preprocessing, we do the georeferencing.
The georeferencing workflow determines the latitude and
longitude values of a collection site using the
available locality information.
It queries geo names, Wikidata, or Wikipedia for
matching geographic entities, starting from the most specific
location and progressing to the least specific.
So from the nearest named place down to the
continent level.
Candidate entities are then scored using multiple evidence
signals, such as name similarity and geographic hierarchy.
The best matching candidate is selected, and its coordinates
are retrieved. If no suitable match is found, the latitude and
longitude are left blank.
Given these sample locality values, our georeferencing method
first searches using the most specific locality, which
in this example is Mount Mozenberg from the nearest named place
field.
Since no match meets the required scoring threshold,
the method proceeds to the next locality level,
Mozenberg, from the township field.
A suitable match is found at this level, and its
corresponding latitude and longitude values are retrieved.
We compared three knowledge bases, geo names, Wikidata,
and Wikipedia. We evaluated the methods using
100 randomly selected site records from the UK data set.
The evaluation data set was manually annotated
using Wikidata, Wikipedia, and Google as
reference sources. Accuracy was measured based on
whether the predicted coordinates were within a 0.1
degrees threshold of the manually identified
coordinates.
We have observed that the three knowledge bases have different
strengths and limitations. Geo names
performs well for administrative and hierarchical place
names but has relatively limited content and a
strict geographic hierarchy.
Wikidata provides
broader coverage, particularly for natural and
general geographic features, although its hierarchy
data can be noisy.
While Wikipedia offers the most comprehensive
information, but searches tend to be noisier
and slower, often returning multiple irrelevant
articles.
Finally, the human-in-the-loop tool for manual corrections,
which looks like this one.
So the list of site records is displayed in the left panel
here. A sample map is also provided to
visualize the corresponding latitude and longitude values
for each site.
By clicking on a site record in the left panel, its detailed
information is displayed, such as this one
on the right.
The original values are displayed.
The column next to it are the suggested values,
and the tool allows users to review and correct the suggested
locality values.
For evaluation, 263 site records were
manually annotated. Of this, 50 records
were used as a training set, while the remaining
213 records were used as the development set.
Before preprocessing, 134
records or site records had only one populated
locality field. After preprocessing, this
number was reduced to 10 records. At the same time,
the number of records with four or more populated
locality fields increased substantially from
13 to 142, demonstrating the
improvement in locality data completeness.
I will show a few examples to illustrate the difficulty of this task.
In this example, the suggested value and the manual annotation may
appear similar, but they are not exactly the same, such as
in this example. For example,
here the province
Western Cape, while the annotator
provided City of Cape Town for this field.
So they're not the same, but then they somehow refer to
Cape.
This is how the record appears in the tool.
And if a locality field is corrected,
such as in this example, the user can rerun the
georeferencing process using these corrected
values.
Clicking the Run Georeferencing button
triggers the georeferencing process, and a pop-up window then
displays the newly suggested coordinates, allowing the user
to either accept or disregard the suggestion.
Here is another example,
and
it looks like this. It's like this in the tool.
That ends my presentation. Thank you for your attention.
This work was supported by an Early Career Research Fellowship
2024 to 2025 program grant. The title is
Enhancing Environmental Resilience through
AI-Driven Analysis of Unstructured Data.
The fund is from the International Science
Partnerships Fund, delivered by the British Council.
Again, thank you very much, and you may send me an email if you have any
questions.
Thank you, Rosalind.
Rosalind is online if there are any questions.
I don't see any hands. We will continue with the next speaker, Brooke
Longfox.
Hi, everyone. Thanks for joining me today.
So I'm Brooke Longfox. I'm a data curation scientist at MorphoBank.
It's a paleontological and biological database, and I'm here today
to share some of our lessons learned from some data extraction that we
did.
So as everyone knows that large language models can now draft structured
biodiversity data at a scale that would've been extremely difficult to achieve
manually. And that creates a major opportunity for repositories, but we
still need to be vigilant and validate the data to make sure that it reflects the
original meaning.
So what we did here,
like I mentioned, I work for MorphoBank, and this is a database that
houses morphological character matrices.
These are used in tree building. And so for example,
the data comes from published papers that are examining
relationships between organisms.
The data that we have specifically in MorphoBank and that we are digitizing,
and adding to MorphoBank is these matrices.
Really, they just look like zeros, ones, and twos in rows and columns.
But they have more meaning behind that, and that's what I'm going to
go into a bit today.
And so what this looks like is this image on the left.
We can see that there is
rows here, and in these rows, there are the different organisms.
So for example, fish, frog, lizard, cat.
And then we have the different columns that describe those organisms, such as
four limbs, amniotic egg, hair.
So for example, let's look at amniotic egg.
We have zero for absent and one for present.
So if an organism has this feature, then it would get a one.
If it doesn't, it would get a zero. And so this is scoring.
So the fish would be zero, the frog is zero, but a lizard and cat is
one. And so the data that we have in MorphoBank looks like this.
The zeros, ones, they're associated with organisms, with specimen names,
and they're associated with different characters and character states.
We also have the capability to add images.
And so you can actually show what that looks like.
So the data that I've been working on adding and that
people add as part of their research are these matrices that are just zeros,
ones, twos, threes. It could be any kind of characters.
What this translates to in the published research is a tree,
where it shows relationships between organisms.
So
a little bit about the kind of data that we put into MorphoBank and how we
ended up deciding to use LLMs to help us curate data.
So what data are in MorphoBank? There's over 1,000 phylogenetic
matrices. We're actually up to
over 1,500 now.
We have a global user community, and
the data in MorphoBank represents hundreds of,
or really thousands of published research articles from hundreds of journals.
Here is an example of what the data looks like in MorphoBank, and so like I said,
there's zeros, ones, twos. There can be question marks, dashes, if you're
unsure or if it's inapplicable.
Unsure would be a question mark, inapplicable would be a dash.
But this is a real dataset, so these are real taxa over here.
The daggers are for the extinct ones, and then the different
characters.
That's the same
matrix looks like,
but with some media, and so
basically people can add their media or, and
even make labels on it, so they can say, "Okay, this taxa
has this specific character, so I'm going to add an image of that character, and
then have a label pointing to it to give information about what that character
might look like."
Okay. So part of what I do is
add
data that's not in MorphoBank. One of the things that we did a
couple of years ago is we got US National Science Foundation funding,
to add, it was around 600
files that came from PBdb to MorphoBank.
Ago, we were adding this manually.
So
once we added in the Nexus files that we were given, we realized that some of the
character metadata was missing. So the character might be
there, so it might say this up here, type of stellate
architecture,
but the specific what does zero, what does one, what does two
mean was missing. And so, for example, this here, it says present.
That is the
character information, and so that information was missing.
So what we did is we then would add the Nexus files that we were
given, so that's the raw matrix files, and then we would need to go
find the published journal article and pull the character information.
And how we did this was we would look at the journal article,
look at the supplementary data,
or look at the tables, and then we would type this in or copy and paste.
And frankly,
for some of these, maybe there's only 20 characters,
but some of these matrices have hundreds or even thousands.
And so this could take anywhere between one to two hours to
frankly
up to 10 or more hours. And so after doing this a couple of times,
we decided that it would be best to try AI and see if that could help us
at least translate the character information into the computer.
What we ended up doing is we had one of our interns, Shreya Jariwala, at UC
Berkeley. She joined us, and she had already helped curate some of this data,
and we had been curating it for a while.
And so
we decided to try out
an AI character or data extraction feature.
And so she was interested in developing this, so she helped us develop this beta
version, in which we used a training set of
20 to-- We started off with 20. I think it ended up being
50 of these data sets. And so we had
already transferred,
we had already
curated, physically typed in, and then copied and pasted and
finalized numerous ones of these. So that's what we used to train the AI on.
So what we did was we took the Nexus files from PBdb, and then we went and found
the journal article, and we took that as well.
And we looked through,
and we tried to find where the character information was.
And for the AI, what we did is we uploaded the Nexus file.
We uploaded the information that needed to be taken
out and added to that Nexus file.
And we had AI do it and add it to the Nexus file.
Part of this process was that the AI wasn't
necessarily finding
the right information, so it wasn't finding the character state information.
It may have found another table or something else that that was similar to, and it
would try to extract that. So then we were at the point where we had to say,
"Okay, it's just these pages in this PDF" or "Let
me just add
just a couple of pages" or tell the AI, "Look at pages five to
six, and that's where the information is." And, "Also here are the number of
characters. There should be 52 characters." So then
the LLM could go in and say, "Okay, let me make sure that that's matching up."
And this was trial and error over the course of about a year
to get this to work.
And so if you want, we have a preprint out in BioRxiv.
We've implemented this beta version in MorphoBank.
And so now, besides us as curators, we can have
users and scientists go in.
They can add their matrix, and if their matrix is missing that
character information,
then they can add that character information and extract it themselves using our AI
technology.
We have this option here. They just add in the file, and then
it takes a couple of minutes if it's
a normal size matrix. This one's
27 characters, for example, were found after it went through the AI, so that was
just a minute or two.
If it's massive, it takes a lot longer.
Anyway, so
basically,
we also have a warning here that the characters were extracted using AI and may
contain errors. Please review them carefully before proceeding.
We have this in there because, with our experience, we have
found errors in almost every single one.
For instance, here is that example of something that could happen.
Over here, okay, we have character one.
Character one, the sifuncle.
The character is located ventrally or displaced laterally. That sounds fine.
Then the two options, zero or one. Zero being ventrally, one being displaced
laterally. Then for character two, we have external lobe shape.
So then all of these states should describe that external lobe shape.
We have zero, one, two, and three.
Zero and one are missing.
Two is bifid. Three is trifid.
The fact that there is no zero or one is concerning.
So
if an author is uploading their information, they should check to make sure
that this is right. Is the zero and one really supposed to be blank?
That would be strange for research.
So I would go in and double-check and okay, well, if it is really blank,
then determine
what we could put in that place to notify other users when they go to reuse
this matrix that that is indeed accurate.
So anyway,
part of us doing this
is that we've ended up processing over 400 papers,
and so we've added over 400 matrices.
So this ended up being roughly 35,000 character state entries.
We estimate that the accuracy is 90%.
But like I said, most of the time
everything is right, but there are minor errors here and there.
And there are some things that could get confusing.
Because some of these papers
could be 30 years old, or copies, or scans of things
They're not always clean PDFs that the AI can read.
But in order to make the data fair, we want to make sure that everything is
accurate and it can be reusable.
So that's why validation is needed.
So our main lesson learned from using the AI is it made the process so
much quicker. So I
added a data set, I wasn't hand-curating it, and it could have taken three
hours. This was now done in three minutes. That's great.
But I still had to go through
and double-check and validate that everything was translated correctly.
And if something did show up, I needed to fix that.
A couple of the things that happened
were some of the problems that we found were omissions and dense or irregular
tables.
Tables can be hard for the LLM.
Heading misalignments. So changing
that example I showed you where the zero and one were empty and then two and
three were there. Well, maybe that two and three should have actually been zero and
one.
So things like that. There are fabricated states.
So
there are a couple random times where
we double-check, we make sure, okay, this is the data.
We're giving it the right data, and for some reason,
there's a couple spots in there, and they'll be in a line, like five different
characters in a row that are just completely made up.
Maybe it's from another paper, I don't know, but something was just completely made
up. So yeah. Fabrication happens and you really have to
double-check everything to make sure that it doesn't wrongly get published and
shared.
Then there's ambiguous anatomical terminology resolved incorrectly.
So this is things where
with biological data, there's very precise words for things, and
the AI doesn't necessarily know those words.
But as an expert or someone who
studies biology or who may know something about birds or clams or
trees, you can catch those and say, "That's not the right word.
You changed that word to something that was more common."
But no, actually, it is that odd spelling,
because that word has meaning.
So what we ended up getting out of this is that validation is needed.
So the automation of AI is great. It accelerates the
drafting, but that is what it is. It's drafting.
And so
it's very exciting to get to use it and to curate much faster.
But it's not a final product.
So AI enables a very
nice rough draft.
But it still needs someone to go through, a human, and validate it.
And this is to make sure that when we're sharing this data, it can be reused
by other people, and it doesn't have all these errors in it.
So some of the things that we learned is that standards make the biodiversity data
exchangeable. The curation and people looking at it
helps keep them scientifically meaningful.
So that's a bit summary of our project and what we've been doing with
AI, and I really thank you for being here to hear about it.
And as we continue to test this out and improve our AI model, and
improve what we're sharing on MorphoBank so that other people can use it, and
maybe one day it will produce perfect matrices.
But I think it needs a lot more time and a lot more training datasets to make
that happen.
Thank you, Guru.
That was the last presentation in this session, and I would like
to thank all of the presenters.
I specifically
enjoyed this session and the previous session
in this conference very much. And
if you are interested, we will have an
unconference at 1:00 PM in the
afternoon after lunch.
Check the
Unconference WHOA application, and I
would like to thank all of the speakers again.
Thank you all for attending.
to 2, audio in, yeah.
Probably three or four.
That's okay. Probably we can have
two of those hands-free mic.
Yeah. We can manage with the other two.
Whatever.
Sorry? You want me to do this? No, just help me with one of those.
Yeah.
Yep. Oh, no.
Sorry?
Yep.
Sure. Thank you.
Hello.
Say that again.
Do we have time for coffee or we're starting?
I don't know. Yeah, you can make it. Just rush.
Rush.
Don't tell me. Don't tell me.
Bye-bye. Good luck. Thanks. Good to see you, man.
I'll see you next time on our line, or we keep in touch.
Let's keep in touch, please. Absolutely. Yeah.
Enjoy. Yep. Bye-bye. Thank you.
Are you going?
Yes. Going. Back to my-
It's safe to order now.
To his privacy.
There you are.
We need Thomas.
Are we using that
one?
This is working.
Is it on? Okay.
It is on, yeah. How are you feel comfortable?
And we have these.
I'm happy with the free hands,
so I can tell jokes and use the hands.
I was going to say, would you rather have this one?
Or you like that as well?
I am already wired.
Huh?
Oh, you're already wired.
Yep.
Oh, I see now. Okay.
Yeah.
Yeah. Different styles.
Greetings, IT.
Hello.
Testing one, two. Yay. Thank you very much.
Nicky, did you want to test that one?
Hello, hello.
Okay.
Hi, everybody. Welcome.
Come in, come in.
Okay. Well, while I call you.
Greetings.
Ah! Well, let me... Here, let me take this thing off.
The moment we have been waiting for.
So much
pressure.
Come in.
Good to go?
I believe so.
Yep.
Anyone? Yeah.
All right
Sorry. Yes, I think so.
Yep.
Yes.
Can someone please help me to shut some of the doors?
Some.
Some, and some not. Not all of them.
The ones at the back.
Yeah, there you go.
And again,
if you have some colleagues scattered around, please ask them to come to
Soul
A. We are going to be using B and C later on.
All right.
Hello, everyone. If you are here on day five in the afternoon,
thank you. I know this is the moment you have been waiting for.
This is Unconference for TADWIC 2026.
If you still don't know me, my name is Javier Molina,
and I am here today with my colleagues.
And
I want to get it right.
Sorry. Some glaze. This is a good start.
We have here Deb Paul. We have Chandra Earl sitting at the back.
Shelley James, where are you, Shelley?
Okay. Well, she will be with us in a moment.
Esteban Marentes
at the back also helping me.
And
my gosh, my apologies, Nikki. I omitted your name.
Nikki Nicholson also helping us here.
So we are your organizers for this Unconference.
Before I go any further, again, I want to appreciate
all the help from our sponsors.
Basically,
you have them here on the screen. So
thanks for showing them your love throughout the conference.
So how this is going to work, essentially.
Firstly, can you raise your hand if this is your first Unconference?
A few hands up. That's really good. Yep. Thank you.
And please remind me who that is still around, this is
your first TADWIC.
Yep, quite a few people. Congratulations. This is going to be really interesting.
Thank you.
So what we are going to be doing here, roughly, this is
the agenda of what we are going to be covering, give or take.
But I'm going to run you through more details, but you will see roughly
what is happening and when. And again, these are not very strict times,
but it is going to keep us basically stay on track and
let you basically go out to have your break.
So essentially, how this is going to work, or what is
Unconference? Unconference, basically, this is the space where you
will be able to talk about those topics that were of your
interest, whatever you learned throughout the conference, but it didn't make
it to a presentation, or it is an idea that
basically you got that seed out of one of the presentations that you
saw throughout the conference. So, and with that
idea,
you will find precisely that there are more people that will share
that. Being that, well, some of the presentations I was in, it
was, for example, camera
trap data package, I think I heard more than once.
Probably it is still not very suited or it can be improved for
insects. So just to give you an idea.
I don't know what were the latest developments on eDNA.
And I know everybody's talking now about Darwin Core data packages
and more semantic models. So I think there is good room to
continue those conversations. So this is the space indeed.
This is your space where you can propose those topics.
Throughout the conference, we have been reminding people to
put those ideas on a spreadsheet. And given here the time, I think
it's going to be tight, but my colleague Nikki will
be calling precisely that people that propose those
ideas to come here and pitch those ideas.
So
basically, that is what we have. And
again,
why we do that? As I mentioned, we have here the space. This is for you.
And the idea is precisely we need to be deliberate to start those
conversations because we want to see what comes out of it.
Whether you start a new interest group, or you didn't know basically
there were more people interested in that and you can make it grow,
that would be a fantastic outcome.
So
essentially, how we are going to work, pretty much,
I am asking, obviously, people online are joining via Whova.
Over there, you should have a link to join Zoom.
So we will use that later on. So the rest is
pretty much here in the agenda.
As I was mentioning, my colleague Nikki is going to be calling everybody
that proposed those ideas on the spreadsheet to come and present those
ideas. It's going to be tight, but
we are going to make it. After that, once everybody has pitched those
ideas, we will have a voting, essentially.
You here, people online are going to vote precisely for those
topics.
And once we decide on the criteria, given the time, probably,
and
how many people are interested, we'll have, I don't know, from four to
eight groups, give or take, precisely to break out
into discussion groups.
And those breakup discussion groups, we are going to use the space that we have
here. This is the moment where we can use Soul B or C
to spread out. But this is a requirement.
One of you, please, needs to have a device to connect via
Zoom to join that
discussion and integrate people online.
Also, when we go to those breakout sessions, we will need one
of you to be nominated as a speaker.
That is going to come later as we finish the breakout sessions
to report back on what were the findings, what did you discuss, what was the most
interesting thing, what are you taking as a group as a next
step, or the most interesting idea that you discussed.
So, and that will take us at the end.
Basically, my colleague, Deb, is going to be wrapping up the session for today.
So
please feel free to yell out at any point if you have any questions.
But without any further ado, I'm going to pass over now to Nikki.
Okay.
Thank you.
Thanks, Javi.
Do you want me to stop to this pressure?
Can you hear me with this?
Cool.
So I'm going to invite each of the proposers up to do a 90-second pitch to recruit
people to their topic.
So you're going to have to
come up here and talk. No slides. First one's Maarten.
I'll time you here, and I will be strict.
That one's on.
Ready? Go.
Okay. 90 second is short, but the idea is that we
have seen a lot of AI applied for natural history
collections,
with CETA, the European Consortium of European Taxonomic Facilities.
We have a group
on AI and robotics that meets three to four times a week.
But we actually envision some kind of living document,
where we collect use cases of AI,
exchange ideas, but also try to get some guidelines, because I've
seen a lot of interesting talks this week, and everyone
has other ways of having quality control on this,
or how do we integrate this into our CMSs?
So with the CETA ISTC, we want to come up with some kind of
guidelines document that helps newcomers,
or collections that don't have experience
on using AI for their digitization to have something to
get back to. And also to have the contact information of those
institutions that do have
experience already. So if you want to have a discussion session,
but also add your use case in a living document on how
you use AI and how you see this evolving in the
future, please join me.
And I still have time left.
Perfect. He has 10 seconds left.
You can clap for his 10 seconds.
Next, we have Quentin.
Hi.
So
European, North American rich country herbariums have a
massive legacy of specimens from all over the world, and
digitization is going ahead in many of them. Many of it is finished.
In some cases, people are thinking about it.
And one of the big drivers behind that is to share all of that information on the
world's floras to the rest of the world.
But it's quite evident the people who are really benefiting from all this
digitization are actually the same rich countries that digitized in the
first place and collected all these specimens from everywhere.
So I feel we have a moral right to make sure that everybody benefits,
especially the countries where most of these specimens come from.
But we also now have a legal obligation, too, through the Nagoya Protocol,
and I want to look at
access and benefit sharing. What are the benefits of a herbarium?
How can we share them with the people
where all these specimens come from?
So I'm pitching for a cost action, which has to be submitted in
October. It was submitted last year.
It failed to get a
high enough score to get funded, but we were close.
I would like to make it a better proposal this time around, and I want you to
contribute to
help that process. I have bribes. If you come, you will get
a Teddy Friends pen and lots of Post-it notes to write on.
Thank you.
That's right.
Well done, Quentin.
Moises is doing well. They both saved 10 seconds.
Next is Deb.
Deb's going to waste her 10 seconds by coming up from the back.
Thank you. Hi, everybody. So you get the moving presentation.
I'm trying-
I'm starting now. So...
Okay. I was trying to solve the tech issue.
So I have had a leadership role in the form of member-at-large for
the Society for the Preservation of Natural History Collections, and I have
also served as past chair of TADWIG.
And in that role, we have memorandums of understanding between the two
organizations. It's very gentle.
It's very loose. I would like to see it become a little bit
tighter in the form of things like, for example, I think
one requirement is that there be a report to each other's organization
for whoever the representative from TADWIG is for SPNHC
and vice versa. And I would like to see that become a little bit more formal, where
we could understand that
TADWIG would do something at SPNHC every year, and SPNHC would do
something or with TADWIG every year in a more
formal way to promote the obvious connections between the natural
history collections world, the data that they generate for all of us to
use, and
the world of TADWIG, and how we can help them do what they want to do
and dream big. So if you'd like to talk more about that and you have ideas for how
to make that happen, that's my pitch.
Well done, Deb.
Can I invite Tim
or Brigitta?
Time's there.
90 seconds.
Go.
Okay. Hi.
I'm pitching a session on causal modeling in ecology.
There are a few talks that circled around this, including my own.
I'm part of a collaboration called EcoWeaver, along with three other
people who are here, and we've been working on causal modeling in ecology
for a few years now.
We're still open to experimentation and exploration, so
it would be cool to get some people together in a room and talk about approaches to
modeling causality in structured ways that could be
useful for informing statistical analyses or digital twins.
So if anyone's interested, come on.
40 seconds. That's pretty good.
Well done
Sam.
Yeah.
Hi, everyone. I've seen lots of excellent presentations
in the past week, and one particular interest of mine as a developer
of information systems is controlled vocabularies.
I've seen them in lots of different sessions, but it's still hard to
find them. When actually my colleague, Miriam, she's sitting over there, asked me a
while ago, "What are the main vocabularies that are playing in the field?"
I had to
form a list in my head, and there is no discoverable place of where we can
find things. So TADWIG is suggesting controlled vocabularies as separate default
terms, and there are a couple within TADWIG, there are a couple in other core, but
there are also others now being developed in the Paleo group, in the mineralogy
extension, they have controlled vocabularies.
New York has some controlled vocabularies.
I was wondering if we could make them more discoverable so that they're easily
accessible.
That's the pitch.
50 seconds.
Next year, we can have them even shorter. Can I invite Claudio, please?
Sam, I have ideas for you.
Hi, everyone. So during these days, there have been quite some
talks speaking about traits, in particular,
text mining to get traits,
but most of the standards right now are available for occurrence data
and
presence/absence, but not that much standardization is available for trait
data. And we are in a moment where there is a
proliferation of trait databases, but they all use different
structures. And the other proponent that is not here, but is connected online,
just created a trait thesaurus for all aquatic
animals. And we thought that these semantic artifacts could be a starting
point towards standardization and somehow
improving the interoperability of traits across realms.
So if anyone is interested in joining the conversation, here we are.
50 seconds.
Thank you very much.
Next, we have Daniel, please.
Hold on.
Okay. So I'm here to invite you to think about how
we should name river basins in a standardized fashion so that it can
be used in biological contexts. I gave a talk about this yesterday, so
we have some basic ideas.
The very rough gist is in the geosciences, they use
spatial grids for everything,
but biology doesn't necessarily follow those grids.
If there is an invasion going on
of fish, they don't orient themselves by the grid cells, but
they follow the water, basically.
And
if we look at this from a global perspective, we have lots of
different rivers, we have multiple languages, we have different
measurement systems and all these kind of things.
And so the idea is to bring this all together and think about
which TADWIG structures could be useful to address this, and
also which other structures, in particular Wikidata, could be
useful to address this. Yeah. And if that's of interest to you,
please join us. Thanks.
Thanks, Daniel.
Can I invite Yasin or Hank?
Okay, you can come along later.
Yasin, your turn.
Quick.
Straight on stage. Quick.
This is for the-
Yep
... unconference?
For your unconference pitch. There you go.
Hello, everyone. Yasin Bakis, Tulane University.
So
my
topic is image quality and AI readiness, and this
is a task group, a new task group in TADWIG.
And then,
since this year TADWIG's theme is about
AI readiness,
I thought we should define what it is and what
dimensions are involved in that. So
we are trying to
get together some group of people,
so that we can understand what this is, and
eventually, this group will publish the results, the
definition specifically, and the dimensions that affects
the
AI readiness of datasets and workflows.
Thank you.
Thank you. Next, we have
Siobhan.
I'm guessing it's going to be Wikidata.
See the time?
There you go.
Hi, I'm Siobhan. There's been multiple presentations touching
on Wikidata, so I just thought I'd offer a space for everyone who
wants to talk about biodiversity data in Wikidata, its
problems, its solutions, its reuse.
So if anyone wants and interested in discussing that, please join me.
Okay. Siobhan is definitely the fastest. That was 20.18 seconds.
Okay, next it's me. I will be strict with myself.
My topic is called Closing Time, and it's about succession planning, disaster
management, and ending projects.
So, it's a sad fact that we do have to end the things that we do sometimes.
And, a colleague of mine who set up The Carpentries initiative,
Greg Wilson, has written a one-day outline of things that one
should consider when a project shuts, and it might be a sudden thing,
or it might be a gradual thing. But how do we look after the knowledge that has
been generated through that project and look after the people, and
package it up neatly so that someone else can pick it up, or it can be ...
stored nicely. So if that's something that you think is relevant for this
community, then yeah, get in touch with me and we'll talk
about it here.
I didn't go over time.
Okay, next we have Ruqayyah one.
You have to get up.
You have to get up. Oh, no, you don't.
No, I'm just-
Can I get in mine?
Ruqayyah has two, I don't know which one you want to choose.
Do I have to choose one?
Yeah, you can choose.
Okay. Also, I'm very interested in the,
what makes data AI-ready one. So
I sort of have three that I'm interested in.
So for the first one I put on the spreadsheet,
I was thinking an informal discussion about Darwin Core data packages might be
interesting.
So I have a chatbot called ChatIPT, which makes Darwin Core
data packages now. And,
as I start looking at real-world examples, there are some
interesting situations I've come up with which might be
cool to discuss with everybody else who's come up with similar
situations.
So that's one.
And then the other one is, there are a lot of
presentations about people who have
done work taking unstructured data or
images of
specimen labels or whatever and extracting it
and
getting structured data. So
people are using all sorts of different methods.
I thought it would be interesting to have a discussion about that as well.
Thanks, Ruqayyah.
I think that's it for our list. We've probably got time if
anyone-
Yeah. If you want to call anyone.
Is there anyone who wants to come from the floor to pitch?
No.
Okay.
We are done. Thanks for that, Nikki. All right.
Can you hear me?
Yes, you can. Okay, so I think now Stefan is coming here
to work with the voting.
So essentially, you already heard all the pitches,
so this is the moment of truth.
People online also, please, this is the moment where you need
to join Zoom
because the voting-- Well, basically, you're going to use your thumbs up
in Zoom, precisely, for your voting.
And it is also important to be mindful of that, every time that
we post that voting, and Stefan is going to be looking after that very carefully.
Unfortunately,
people joining online are living slightly in the past, so there is a
10-second delay on the streaming.
So by the time we vote, we need to wait to give them some time
to emit their vote. So over to you, Stefan.
Okay.
This one doesn't work. Okay, yeah.
Sorry. Yeah, go ahead.
Okay, so it's voting time.
We're going to start with the first pitch.
You can vote three times. I know all the topics are really
interesting, but you can only vote three times.
I will not be counting who votes, but I trust everyone here.
You just raise your hand, and I count you really fast, and I count the
people online really fast. So if you are hearing us
online, please join on Zoom, and when the topic comes,
you raise your hand on Zoom.
The first topic was AI for natural science collection
for Martin. So who wants that to be a topic?
Three,
four,
17.
Anyone online?
18.
No online votes. Okay, 18.
Next topic,
botanical legacies reimagined by Quentin.
Who wants to vote?
3, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13,
14.
14. Anyone online?
No. 14.
Okay.
Next one, the one by Dev, enhancing
cross-connectivity between SBNACH and Tadwait.
Who wants to vote for that?
3, 4, 5. Okay. I'm going to support you, Dev.
5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.
People online, you should vote. I'm starting to worry about-
Just give them time.
Yeah.
Marie, can you vote?
So just say no. You hear me?
Okay. So
10 for that.
Then we have the one for Sam. Controlled vocabularies,
where do they live? Who wants to vote for that?
Oh,
pretty good.
Nice.
Five.
It's old.
31. Wow, that's pretty good.
Any vote online for that topic?
Okay.
We have the causal modeling.
It's the fifth one.
Number 11.
Oh, yeah
Because it's in another place.
The one from Bridget, Casual Modeling in Ecology for
Biodiversity.
Who wants to vote for that?
13 here.
Okay.
It's online.
Good. Chandra?
The Zoom online died?
Yes.
All right. Okay. Well, this is real life. Just give us a few seconds.
For people online, please bear with us.
We are trying to sort out the issues with the Zoom connection.
I trust you still are following us on Vimeo or on the Whova app.
All right. It's back again and people are joining, so let's give it-
Oh, it's back?
Yeah, but they kicked out everyone.
Oh, yeah.
So we're just waiting the precious seconds.
I think you want to try from here.
That is what we are seeing.
Okay.
So we have some people back online.
The next topic is from Claudia. What about
traits?
Who wants to vote for that?
11.
12.
One online.
Next one we have the one from Daniel and Vanessa.
River-based naming.
Next step is in Taguidt. Who want to vote for that?
Two,
three.
Anyone online?
Okay.
The one from Jason and Hank. What makes biodiversity data
AI ready?
Who wants to vote for that?
18, and two online, 20.
Siobhan, Wikidata.
18.
Anyone online for Wikidata?
That's an online topic.
I'm voting for that.
Nikki, closing time, about closing the projects.
Who wants to vote for that?
21, and one online, 22.
The next, Rukaya. First Darwin Core data package.
Who wants to vote for that? Please, people, that's the one I want.
14. Three online. You can check online. There are three votes, really.
It's not me just
putting all votes in my topic.
Okay.
The last one about Rukaya.
Comparing how everyone extracts EXTRUD data from Staf.
Who wants to vote for that?
Three. Rukaya, you want to vote for your topic?
Okay.
So we have the voting.
Now we choose how many topics?
Now we need to choose, basically, give or take.
Let's say roughly the numbers of votes.
We have 17, 14. The biggest one was 32.
30-something, yeah.
They could have a room of their own.
Yeah.
And I don't know how you feel, probably.
We could have-
Let's keep the goals five, six. Rekar?
Yeah. Five. Okay.
We have four topics that has more than 20.
Those.
Going for sure. And next we have a tie between
AI for natural science collections and
Darwin Core data package.
Oh.
And I don't feel unbiased enough to break that tie.
I think we can do both.
Okay.
If we have room for the six sessions?
Yeah.
We do.
Yeah. Let's do the six sessions.
Okay. Then we are having six session, people.
Yep.
Would you mind summarizing again what are the six sessions, please?
AI for natural science collection for Martin.
Martin, where are you? Okay. So
Yeah, we have-
We have Boulder.
Yeah, the question is how much we want to spread all the people? Yeah.
Absolutely.
Okay, Martin. So you can go
in that corner, the first good corner.
Next, we have controlled vocabularies, Sam.
So you can go that corner at the back.
Yeah.
Just to start spreading people. After that, we can
move to another one.
Yes. Remember, follow your leader.
Yeah. If you know you want AI for natural science collections,
you know where you want to go. Vocabulary is over there.
Yeah. Can you give me just a second?
And for people online, please
let Chandra know which one you want to join in Zoom.
She will organize the break rooms appropriately.
In the meantime, for the different groups, please remember you need to join
a Zoom meeting for each of the sessions.
So if you can organize in your group who is joining Zoom to integrate online
participants, that would be awesome.
Thank you.
Jason, where are you?
Next topic, can you come here in the middle?
Next topic is what makes biodiversity data AI-ready.
Wikidata, Siobhan,
can you go in the back?
Next, we have Nikki. Where is Nikki? There.
Nikki, can you go over there? Thank you very much.
And next we have Rukaya with Darwin Core
data package, and we can meet in that corner.
But also we can move around.
Yeah.
We can move around. So
now you can start moving people, looking for where you want to be
in the discussion.
We have the six ones?
Yes.
Okay. Sorry. Hold on. Before you go,
please remember we have enough room here.
We have still B and C to move around.
But before we go, I'd say let's give it 30 minutes or
so. You can have your discussions, and after those 30 minutes,
you can come back 2:05 here to reconvene.
And remember, you need to choose who will be the person that will
represent your team to come and talk.
Not necessarily has to be the
person that proposed the idea, but you need to select one.
And please remember, join the Zoom meeting in each of the different groups
so Chandra can integrate the people online.
So see you here at 2:05. Thank you.
Okay.
Here we are.
Can we start preparing to wrap up?
I know the conversations are still going,
and we could be here the whole afternoon, but
it is time to start wrapping up, please.
I trust you already have some representative to come and share the
summaries.
Mm-hmm.
I will give you some minutes to settle back in, but if you can start wrapping up,
please, your discussions,
and prepare those summaries, it'll be awesome.
Mm-hmm.
Almost there.
For people online that already left their Zoom session, some of the groups are
still trying to wrap up.
We will be there with you shortly.
All right. How did it go?
Fantastic.
So let's continue moving along.
And let me find that spreadsheet.
Stefan, you will have to help me just to validate that these are the sessions we
had, six sessions, six discussions. The top six.
One, two, three, four, five, six.
All right.
Welcome back, everyone.
So now moving on the agenda. This is a time where I hope
you had really good discussions.
But I'd like to invite a representative from
each of the breakout rooms to come here and give us a summary of
how your conversation went. What
were your takes? What were the main points, and how are you taking
those discussions forward?
Right. Let's
start here from the top. We have Stefan.
Sam?
Come here.
Okay.
Does that work? Yeah.
Also, there is some small things from GBIF,
our brand new-- We have a couple in the booth, but they
were really the best selling, so there are none left, just these
ones from the speakers.
So you get two
Pins, things,
beautiful things.
One candy from Colombia, from Bocadillo.
So that's for you for coming here to present,
and also for all the presenters.
So we are just announcing that, so you didn't know just for the prize.
Thanks, Stefan. So I think the best thing is
just a picture from there?
Okay.
So, yeah.
Yeah. I would do some.
Yeah. So controlled vocabularies.
Clearly, there's a lot of interest in it, as we were the highest
voted topic.
And we had a nice group. We sat in the corner.
So one of the things that quickly came out is that actually the data
quality group, where Arthur and Lee were present,
have already made an inventarization of all the controlled vocabularies and came up
with a list with over 100 controlled vocabularies that are now active.
So clearly a lot of work on that part is already being done.
But yeah, we need to finish those lists.
They're nodding, so I'm saying the right things.
And then
make sure that it's discoverable and people know about it.
So that's one part. The other part is that there is already tooling
to map between vocabularies and people working on creating these
tools.
So that's really interesting, and see if we could integrate those
as well. And, of course,
GBIF has 25 concepts
there already, which we might see if we can work further
upon and further improve them and get them potentially to a higher level
so that we will get concepts and RDF in there.
The conclusion became more and more that there's enough interest to
start an interest group. So we've collected email addresses, and we'll reach
out to-- Oh, I might need to
touch something.
Yeah.
And get an interest group growing.
So if you're interested,
I have a pen and paper there. It might be a bit old school.
Or send me an email and I will add you to the list and see if we can
start a discussion on different topics.
Debbie requested updated lists of unique values that are currently being
used, so we can have a look at those and see if we can use those as starting
points. So,
values that are now being used for habitat or for sex in
GBIF.
See if
we're improving as well, we could use it as a measure.
And, yeah, the Paleo data
work group
that
really helped the Paleo community in setting up controlled vocabularies.
We might see if we could ask them to explain their
process and see if we can copy it to other domains as well.
So it's preliminary work and just getting the discussion going.
But it looks like there's enough interest to set up an interest group within
TWIG and further work on these items.
Thanks, Sam.
Yeah.
Thank you. Now I could tell why Sam's
thing were getting busy, just preparing those notes.
Can you reload that page, please? It shows up now.
Sorry?
Just reload that Google.
Sorry, what is the error? Because I don't want to lose the filters.
There are things in the wrong
rows.
Are they?
Down at the-- It's only the first four columns that are filtered.
So the others are not filtering, so-
Oh, yep.
If you reset the filter, everything is in place.
Yeah. So this is causing some...
Let me see.
Better?
Yeah.
Sorry, guys. Yeah, I wanted your attention on the first four columns.
Oh, no, they're back.
Just ignore it. All right. Okay. Next one.
Can I call Nikki on stage to present? Thank you.
Well, I assume it was you, same names.
I'll look around. Thank you. I was joined by eight colleagues
to talk about
what we think about when we close down projects, and sadly, we all had a lot of
experience of that. I would say that when we
started forming the discussion,
we were really thinking about software and digital projects.
But of course, many of us work in natural history collections, and
Shelley from Perth contributed that they are often asked to
adopt physical collections and the digital resources that go along with them.
So there's considerations that we need to make when someone else's project is
shutting down and we're adopting it.
How we support people that are going through that.
Libby was in our group, president-elect of Spinach, and immediately
being asked to write lots of support letters to other organizations that are
facing difficulties.
And we talked about different kinds of disasters, like
not just the loss of funding, which obviously is quite disastrous, but
really sudden things like hacking,
the things that we might face.
And the kind of things that we need to know within our
organization. So, I'd be interested to know, of the people here, who's got an
up-to-date job description?
Right. So if you disappeared, I don't know how your organizations would
replace the people that they don't actually know what they do.
Who does exit interviews when they have staff leave?
Right.
So you don't know what the people do in your orgs,
and you don't know how to replace them. Right.
I really don't know how we go forward this topic, but it's something that's really
relevant, so we've kept our email addresses, and we'll continue talking to each
other. But,
yeah, I'm sure others, it's relevant for them too.
And yeah, please get in touch with us, and we'll keep on talking about this.
Thanks, Nicky.
Thank you.
All right. I think Stefan has something for you.
Moving along. Different screen, sorry.
Okay, so just double-checking. What makes biodiversity
data robot ready? Standards, infrastructure, and AI.
Is it Yasin who is reporting or someone else?
All right.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Hello, everyone.
So we started working with
about 10 different definitions, and we
ended up with 30 more,
and for the AI readiness. So we couldn't
exactly solve the problem, but we have an
approximated result for the definition.
So
it relies on the
supports
for the datasets.
And the basic definition
is AI readiness is the degree to which a dataset
and its associated workflows can support a
defined AI task reliably, and
those supports
are data structure, metadata
readability, terminology,
metadata completeness and richness, taxonomic
backbone, unique identifiers, fairness,
reproducibility, and plus
task
performance and task specificity,
context information, clear authorship,
usage history, and reliability.
And this is what we come up with so far,
but we will continue with
this group right now. And then we have another group from yesterday.
We will continue working on this definition.
If anybody wants to join, just email me
or find me on Whova.
I am Yasin Bakirci. Thank you.
Thank you, Yasin. You are forgetting something.
Say again?
This is for you.
Present from GBIF-
Oh, this is for us
... and conference.
Yes.
All right. Moving along.
Wikidata et al.
Is that Siobhan? Yeah. Come on stage. There's Siobhan.
Thank you.
Mm-hmm.
So we added a link to our Etherpad, where we recorded a lot of our
discussion into Whova if you want to go to this room, and it's
in the chat.
So the majority of the discussion was about
people in Wikidata.
But specimens and type specimens were also mentioned.
The group raised issues with identifiers such as ORCID and
how Wikidata can assist with resolving such issues, such as multiple
ORCIDs for one person or an ORCID relating to several people.
We discussed the value of adding identifiers into collection management systems
and the challenges of this type of integration, including the capacity of
employees to do this work, resources supporting this work, and whether
the collection management system itself had appropriate fields for people
identifiers. As part of this discussion, we talked about the MIDs,
and the analysis of GBIF records and the lack of use of
recordedBy ID and identifiedBy ID in GBIF.
There's a current Wikidata property proposal
for the GBIF occurrence ID.
And if you are a Wikidata editor and wish to comment on this property proposal, we
encourage you to do so. Again, a link to this proposal is in the
Etherpad, which is linked to in Whova.
And of course, the group definitely wanted to emphasize that Wikidata can be used
for many more things other than people, including expeditions,
specimens, well, type specimens, not specimens in general,
invasive species, and of course, river basins. Thank you.
Thank you. Big smile.
Cool.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
Thank you, Siobhan. Thanks, Stefan.
All right.
Next. AI for natural science collections. Is that you, Martin?
Yeah.
It's you.
Okay, so thank you for everyone that joined.
This time was really way too short to discuss
everything. But we had some kind of initial exchange of what people were
doing in their collections, what they needed.
We had the opportunity also to talk to someone from an HPC
center, how they can play a role in the whole process
of digitizing and transcribing our collections.
There are some possibilities and some potential needs from us that we have
to clearly identify and come back to them to
maybe get something moving.
First of all, I'm here-
Taking the stage, but in the CETAB group, I'm not the only convener of
this group. Arianna Salili James from the Natural History Museum in London is
actually my co-convener, but she had to leave already, so if you have
questions for her, you can also send it to her if you don't want to talk to me.
That's fine. And although we are the European taxonomic
facilities, I really don't want this to be a European effort.
I want it to be global and to bring together
all people that are interested in using AI to digitize their
collections or to enhance the data on their collections.
Normally, we have meetings three to four times a year that
are open for anyone. If you want to join or if you want to be part of
my mailing list, please contact me, then I will put you on our
general mailing list. And I will also put in
the platform the link to our Google Doc, which is
open. If you have use cases that you want to share with us,
or if you have open questions that you don't have an answer to, please add them to
the document, and then we can take it forward from there.
Thank you very much.
Okay. Let's keep going.
Why nobody told me that this phone is too small? I was struggling.
I made it. Probably a little bit better.
Sarah Kaye is coming to stage.
Up to you.
Hi.
Ooh.
Okay. So,
in our group, I had ChatGPT
transcribe our discussion and then come up with
summary points, which I'm just going to read out now.
So we were talking about Darwin Core data packages,
and
we ended up being very GBIF-centric actually in our
discussion,
because we had GBIF people there, but also obviously very relevant.
So,
we were saying that GBIF should not visualize everything and
cannot actually visualize everything when it comes to
data and datasets. It should instead help people find trust,
publish, and access complex data in the form of Darwin Core data
packages.
Complex data packages break the GBIF
index model or are not
currently
ingested properly by the GBIF index model, and
GBIF is going to be working on stronger catalog functions
alongside the index.
We should use data packages when the Darwin Core Archive star
schema doesn't fit for a particular dataset.
And the main blockers with
more people using Darwin Core data packages are
around the tooling and creation,
but also the visualization and review of
them.
And Marie was saying that now is a really good time to test real
Darwin Core data packages because GBIF is
actively working on that at the moment, and
people should contact her if they have good examples.
And we talked about how AI can help with Darwin
Core data package creation,
but only when it is very well prompted with good structure
and particularly good examples,
real-life good examples of data.
And we also talked about having reusable prompts and
pooling our ideas
when it comes to mapping
our real-life data into complex
formats like the Darwin Core data packages.
And then our last discussion point was that the best
model for the future at the moment is to have GBIF for discovery
of data packages and to actually go to the IPT
to access the unadulterated data
and use that in your specialized tool or script or whatever.
I think it did a reasonably good job of transcribing and summarizing everything,
actually. It certainly remembered things better than I did.
Thank you.
Don't go anywhere.
Yep. That's it.
All right.
Unless I got it wrong, I think that is the end of our six--
Did you see my Spanish?
I think that was the end of
the six breakout sessions. So
before moving to the last part of this conversation
for Unconference, I'd like to call to the stage my colleague, Deb Paul,
to do a summary of what happened in this Unconference.
Hi, everybody. Thank you, and thank you for coming.
And for those of you, if this was your first Unconference,
would you do this again? Put your hand up.
Aha, yes. So it also resonates for me.
I'm one of those people that gets a little frustrated by an agenda because there's
no room for the ideas that pop up into your head, right?
And so in a conference, in your events, think about making
spaces for these.
Where's Matt? Where are you?
Yoder, where did you go? He's in the back. Huh?
He's in the back. He's in the back. There he is, okay.
So one of the things he will talk about liking to do, you can imagine if we had
more time now, we would move into something more like hackathon
mode. How many have never heard of that word, hackathon?
New word for you. Yeah. So this idea that now we would do
something Right? So we all learned from each other what was in our heads about
these different topics, which if we hadn't made space for that, we would never
know. Yeah? Instead of having that by-accident
conversation at the water cooler, you make structured spaces for water cooler
conversations to happen by this, right?
And so a hackathon, we would then all now break out into groups that interest us,
and we would try to build something, write something, make something,
design something, make a prototype.
So think about those kind of things in your own organizations when you're designing
meetings and events
now that you've experienced this. There's online documentation for that.
And here you saw the wide variety of topics that came up, and the number
of hands that went up that give you an opportunity to expand on what you
got exposed to here, and what was near and dear to your heart
in that space. So thank you for coming and experiencing this,
and then thank you for being able to take that model into the things that you do in
your community to make more room for more voices to speak up and
contribute
about what's burning a hole in their pocket, so you can find
synergy across your organizations
and across your individual groups. So thank you for that.
So happy to answer any-- Do you have any questions out of curiosity at this
point?
No? I would encourage all of you to think about publishing your outcomes.
You have the journal, this, you have blog posts.
Nikki, what's the one, I'm putting you on the spot, that you wanted to recommend?
Can you
share that one? Because I can't remember. Mm-hmm.
Got a mic or jump up.
Is it on? No?
Testing.
Can you hear me? Yep.
Yeah.
Cool.
Yeah, so we have the opportunity to put an extended abstract into this.
A community that I work with a lot, they do this thing called a
speed blog. So
admittedly, we have more than 40 minutes
for a session in an unconference. Our entire annual meeting is run as an
unconference.
Yep.
But we write the structure of
a blog post
within that discussion time, and then we fill it out over
the next couple of weeks when we've had a little bit of time individually to think
about it, and then we publish it. So I think that's something that would be
interesting for us to look at doing,
either for these ones or next year.
So I have selfishly roped her in to do this, to talk about the point
that you can have more publishing and communications outcomes about what you're
doing and what you're thinking through these kinds of avenues. Right.
So any final other thoughts?
No, I think if we are done, what I want to
say is first, thanks everybody for joining this unconference.
I think it is not easy, precisely at this time of the conference, at this time of
the day.
Still, after probably a week, there are still some remains of jet lag,
so you made it.
What I want to do now, if you don't mind, is say two pieces of marketing.
I'd like to call for everybody that was pitching ideas
to come to stage to have a picture.
Oh.
And followed by that, for whoever is remaining, let's please get
together to take the official conference
photo. All right.
Official photo.
So can we start precisely
with all the people that pitched ideas?
It doesn't happen if you didn't make the cut. It was great that you came here.
And we will need a volunteer to help us with the camera, please.
Where's my camera? Haven't got
it.
Can I have all the co-organizers? Chandra, we need you.
Don't run away.
I don't know where it is. Probably over there by-
Shelley, where are you?
You are not safe.
Oh.
Better make face though.
Better shape than me. Just...
Yeah. Esteban, someone has to help you. You need to come here.
Esteban?
Yeah, Esteban. Yeah, I told him. Esteban?
Dutch reading?
Somebody else can take the picture.
You need to ask someone to help us.
Somebody else take the picture.
Somebody.
Yes.
Elliott.
Somebody's got to have a finger in
that.
They all have fingers.
Right?
Are we ready here? Big smiles for unconference.
Cheese.
Say third week!
Unconference.
Again.
Push. Unconference. No. Say third week. Third week.
Good? Yay. Thank you. Thank you.
Now,
can I ask everybody to come here, to stage?
We will figure out where we will take the picture.
You can.
Please, just come here.
I'll just sit
over here.
Yes, do you need help?
No.
No? Okay.
Help us with the picture.
Could you help us to take a
picture? Thank you.
Hi,
everybody. I
wanted to say please, if you haven't yet had the time or the moment, if you
knew Henry Engledow and you loved him like many of us, please
sign this for his family and his loved ones, if you have not done so
yet. Thank you.
I specifically did not get this because too many people were talking.
What is this thing about?
A gentleman in our community passed away.
His name is Henry Engledow, and I don't know if you knew him.
No.
He was the data manager, data wrangler at Mysore Botanical Garden.
Okay.
And just one of those all-around people that you meet that just because
they're in the room,
you're happier. They're like medicine in the best sense.
Good-tasting medicine that you want more of, right?
He's definitely that kind of person.
It doesn't matter who you talk to who knew Henry, we all say that.
And he definitely was another one of our rare individuals.
We're rare here that we have one foot in the collections world and
one foot in this world.
And so we were the bridges between people who were caring for our historical
natural history collections and taking care, and the people who were trying to not
immobilize the data, which they are very active in doing, and then we're trying to
make that data useful.
And bring in new data, and...
Yeah, exactly. And he did that exceedingly well, and he was a
really good advocate for keeping the work grounded.
Yeah, keeping the work grounded and
for use your own hand, whatever. But keeping the work grounded-
Okay
... by making sure that he says what is important
to
keep in mind for collection managers, the people who are actually doing it.
He was really good for that. So
he's really missed.
All of
the-
Forget the notes and promises.
I won't, I promise.
You're
almost finished. I'm going to take some of this.
Ugh.
It's under.
None of your business.
All right. I will share, absolutely.
All right.
Well, welcome to the end of the week, everybody.
Congratulations, you made it this far. Yeah, absolutely.
This session is going to be a joint business meeting and closing
session. We will attempt to come in as close to
4:30 as possible.
It's not going to happen.
But we'll try to get there. I know that some of you are going to have to leave
midway through. It is perfectly fine. We still love you.
And we'll thank you for coming.
When you get up, we will make sure to embarrass you appropriately.
So we will get started. First thing I want to do, is acknowledge our
sponsors who supported this meeting and the development of
this meeting, GBIF, Picture A, BioShare,
Atlas of Living Australia,
Pensoft, and EarthCube.
Great sponsors, great people to work with, and we're very happy to have had them
in our court
for the last many months.
One quick announcement before I forget,
which I am very liable to do at this point in the meeting.
If you have misplaced something,
whether it be your head or something from your bag or
whatever, please check with the lost and found before you leave,
because after today, it is considered communal property.
So just double-check with the
front desk, the help desk downstairs if you have lost
anything.
And so we will get started. This is what we have to cover, just one or two
things,
in a very short period of time.
And
I think we will do it with as much grace as we can possibly muster.
Photos are welcome,
so please feel free
to do that.
Just to let you know, since this is the business meeting, these are the people that
are responsible for the business of TADWIG.
You'll see in the upper left, we've got the executive
seats. I'm the chair. Ellie Saliba,
where are you, though over there,
is our deputy. Tiri, where are you, Tiri?
There is Tiri, as our secretary for another
little while.
And Chandra, who's in the back, you'll see her in a moment,
is our treasurer. We have
five functional subcommittees. The chairs of those are
listed,
as well as the regional representatives,
over there on the far right for you.
And of course, a couple of ex officio members, Ellie Wallace
and Stan Bloom, who keep us in line when we feel like we're
walking crooked.
So
just very quickly, how many of you are here?
Can you guys stand up and let us know?
There's the executive committee
for TADWIG.
And they put up with me tolerably well.
We'll talk about some of these folks a little bit
farther on in the business meeting.
But these are the folks that if you have questions about TADWIG, ask
A quick couple of announcements about this and over the last
year's
proceedings from Living Data. We had 100
extended abstracts, which is an excellent number.
We would love to see more than that.
The conference, of course, here is just ending, but we would really love for
you to add your extended abstract to the proceedings for this
year. Right now, we have six submitted, which is not surprising given the time.
But one of the advantages of using
or submitting an extended abstract is you don't just have 300 words that
you can submit. You can submit charts and graphs and other appendices,
among other things, as well as a much more extended
description of your work.
It's free for you.
So normally it costs money to do this, but we're covering you.
So it's a free DOI, free publication for you.
So we strongly recommend that you consider submitting
your presentation or poster
from this year as an extended abstract into that publication.
We will be sending out reminders,
because that's what Javier does about getting the word out about this
and those publications in the coming weeks. So do keep an eye out for that.
Also, just to remind you
that if you're interested in working with this as we expand its reach,
and you're interested in some editorial work or other possibilities, please
talk to Ellie. And also, as you are finishing your own
papers and thinking about what journal you might want to publish those papers
in,
we'd be happy to consider your submission.
So, think of all of those things. Is there anything I should add, Ellie?
The
deadline is the 9th of October.
Deadline for extended abstracts is the 9th of October.
Unless you have a whole dozen home-baked cookies and you can
send them to Australia,
in which case Ellie will probably extend you to the 10th.
Okay?
What's that?
Australian time.
Yeah. There you go. Australian time.
All right.
So 26th then.
Yes, absolutely. You got it right. You've been around, haven't you?
All right.
I'm going to step out of the way, allow Chandra
Earl, our treasurer, to come up and present the treasurer report,
in large part because she's one of those people who has to leave a little early.
So here she comes. We should have a theme music for
this.
The screen's down here. Awesome.
Just look
behind you and you'll just see stuff.
All right.
Yeah, I'm sorry.
Okay. I have 10 minutes, and when I originally made these slides, there were like
30 of them.
Met with Dave, and he promptly said, "Hey, you need to cut about half of this." So,
here we go. So, quick updates to TADWIG
policies real quick.
Well, I've spent the last year-ish shadowing Stan, so I've technically
been treasurer for a little over a year now.
But of course, TADWIG has a lot of stuff going on
in treasurer news-ish. So I
gained access to all the accounts, reviewed all the tax documents, et cetera.
But in doing so, I also interviewed treasurers from our sister societies, just to
kind of see, "Hey, what are you guys doing in regards to your money?
How are you investing your money? How are you handling your money?
How are you doing things?" Versus what I've learned about how TADWIG is managing
our finances. And so basically,
what this document is, is I've taken everything that I've sort of learned
and put it all into an accounting and financial policies document.
And the point of all this is to really codify what it is
that we're doing already, but really
write it down and make it so that the knowledge is not just
institutional on one or two people, but to make it a bit easier to
transfer between treasurers over time.
So this
is technically still in draft form.
I'm hoping to get it out by the end of the year.
But if you would like to see and read through it
as it is now, it is a pretty hefty document.
But it will be publicly available on the website
just to be publicly
clear about what our financial policies are and how we as TADWIG, as
a society, work.
All right. Next few slides are just going to be a lot of charts and a lot of
numbers because as treasurer, that's just what I get to look at.
This chart is our individual and
institutional memberships over time.
A real couple quick things to note about said chart
is that we've got the
blue are our individual memberships, and the green are
institutional memberships. In order to put these on the same scale, I've
multiplied the institutional memberships by five because that's
how many we count.
There's five people within an institutional membership, roughly.
And so that's why the green is so much higher than the blue here.
But you'll see that we, on average,
have about 171 institutional times
five,
and 235 total per year, and 64
individual per year.
This then, what's maybe a little bit more important for the treasurer side of
things, is going to be our revenue per year.
So revenue per year, we gain about $18,000 per
year just from membership dues, both from the individual and
the institutional side. And you can see that's kind of fluctuated over the years,
but it's kind of stabilized out in these past few years,
again, to give us around $18,000 a year.
This is the annual meeting net income.
So because our two biggest revenue sources are going to be
from the membership and from the annual meeting, it's
really important that we at least minimally break even on our annual
meetings.
Obviously, we lost a lot of money in Beijing, lost a little bit of money
in Kenya, and you can see that we, for the most part,
do
gain a little bit of money
from the conferences every year.
You'll see Oslo is this big, big bar in yellow.
We're not going to make $177,000 on this event.
This is only because we haven't paid our bills yet.
And so that's why that's in yellow.
Looking at the expenses for this conference, I do expect that we will probably
break even. It'll probably be right around the same as these
others
over the years. But
just to note, yeah, we do gain about another $18,000
per year on average from our conferences.
We have, since partnering with Pensoft and making that contract in
2021, I think,
there's a
little bit of included publishing costs since that time.
And so if you take those out, we only actually get about $10,000
in revenue on average.
I'm not going to go through all of the categories of our expenditures
because there are a lot of them, but I just want to point out that, of course, our
expenditures do change over the years just depending on what it is that we've got
going on.
So you'll see we've paid contractors throughout the years, mostly to make
our website and infrastructure to build that up a little bit.
But that's why there's such a difference in our expenditures.
You can see we've paid a journal editor from 2020 to 2025,
and yeah.
If you only look at the things that have sort of remained the same over the years,
you'll see-- Thank you.
You'll see that on average, our expenditures are around
$7,000 per year without those things that aren't
every single year that we have to pay for.
So all that being said,
our revenue then, our membership gives us that $18,000.
The annual meeting gives us that $10,000, meaning that our total revenue every year
is right around $28,000. And our expenses,
again, right around $7,500. That contract with Pensoft
that I talked about briefly, we have a base fee of around $3,000.
And all this is in USD, by the way, because we are out of California.
It means that our net revenue every single year is right around $17,500, and
that changes, again, wildly, mostly depending on the conference, and again,
who it is that we're paying and what it is that we're doing.
We can see that in our,
what is this, adjusted closing balance every year.
Obviously, we are gaining $17,500 every single year, and so we
see that closing balance going up.
Again, our balances right now for 2026 are quite high, again, because we have not
paid our bills for this conference yet.
But that will decrease in a couple of months here.
You can see that we opened our savings account in 2023, where a lot of that money
was moved from a checking into our savings account.
And so these next couple slides, what I'm going to talk about is, okay, we've got a
lot of money in our savings account.
What can we then do with that money, and how should
we be taking advantage of that to
really make TADWIG financially stable throughout the
coming years? And so these are some of the things that I'm going to be working on
this next year. So here's what I'm proposing,
or here's what I will be proposing to the executive
here in a little bit. So
from our policies document, if you have that open, you can see
that there are some rules around how much money we have to keep in
operating cash and how much money we have to keep in our savings at all time.
Luckily for us, we have a lot of savings. We're okay.
But I'm proposing that we keep
100% operating, which I've calculated out to be $55,500 a
year, which
includes that average operating expenditure of
$7,500 plus an average of how much our conferences
cost us every year. That's how I got that number.
So I'm proposing we keep at least that much in our operating cash at all times.
I'm also proposing that we have another copy of that in
short-term money market funds. And so what that lets us do is it lets us get a
little bit more than the very paltry $75 a year we're
getting from our savings account right now into something a little bit more
fungible, if you will.
But it's still liquid enough that allows us
to be able to get that money if we absolutely need it.
So that's our emergency backup fund.
So essentially, we've got two times our amount of operating costs just
available to us really, really quickly if we need it.
I'm also proposing that we set aside
$50,000 to put in a restricted endowment.
TADWIG does not currently have any endowment funds.
We don't have any endowment accounts.
And so what I think this will let us do is by doing this, it
will
let us
establish those policies for investing, distributing, and using endowment funds,
because you need all three in order to have an endowment,
which will enable us to start making and managing endowment gifts if there are
any.
And so I think that really puts us in a good position to say, "Hey, we have an
endowment. If you would like to make an endowment, we are prepared to
bring that under our wing and then take care of it and manage it in a way that is
nice."
And then we take the remaining $139,000 that we have and stick it into
long-term investments.
And so if we do all of these things that I am
proposing
Well, actually back up just a second.
You'll see that
if you think back to
our individual and institutional memberships, you'll remember that our
individual memberships is actually stagnant.
We're not gaining as many as we probably should.
Our institutional membership is increasing, but again, it's about
0.8 institutions per year is how many we're
gaining every single year.
And if we take the proposed changes that I'm making and we're calculating,
okay,
how much money are we going to get based on those investments?
Of course, we've got our net revenue from our memberships and our
meetings of 17.5. We've got our 2,000 in short-term
investments. That endowment will give us 17.5, and the long-term
investments will give us $21,000.
All this totaling up to say, okay, hey, if we do this, we could be
gaining around $48,000 a year.
So then now the next steps here, okay, what do we do with that
$48,000?
And these are some of the things that
we're going to be thinking about over the next year.
And of course, if you all have any major considerations or would like to be
included in this, please feel free to contact me, contact Stan, any
of the exec. But first, if there's any major thoughts, concerns, or
preferences regarding how the TADWIG funds are invested.
Obviously, we're going to do our best to make sure we are investing in sustainable
practices
that align with our mission and vision.
But if you've got any investment accounts that you particularly
love for whatever reason, again, please feel free to contact me.
Second, how do we leverage money to generate and increase membership? Right?
Our membership is stagnant, so what can we do to leverage this
$48,000 that we're getting to
support our membership, to gain membership?
So these are just two ideas that I had off the top of my head when
writing this. So one, of course, I think a chunk of this needs to go to
support our functional subcommittees, specifically outreach and
visibility, and time and place.
Outreach and visibility, we could potentially pay for them to go to conferences,
do tablings, those sorts of things, really get the word about TADWIG out there.
And then time and place, I'm thinking, okay, it can be really hard to get
hosts for meetings sometimes, even though, of course, we do pay for the full event.
Maybe we can put some sort of honorarium in place or something to
get people to say, "Oh, hey, I would like to have
the TADWIG conference hosted here, please and thank you."
Maybe in order to get more memberships, we need to have more membership-only
materials and programming. Again, when I was talking to all these treasurers, it's
like, how are you maintaining membership?
What is it that your membership gets when they have a membership in
your society? And of course, we can't close off standards behind membership,
so what do we do? And so I was thinking, okay, maybe there are some
things that we can pay
money into to create and develop, and again, put that behind
a membership-only
line.
And then the last thing is for this restricted endowment.
This I think is something really cool and a really cool opportunity that we have as
a society. And so, is this something that we could potentially name
after someone?
Is there specific
things that we can use those funds for?
For example, maybe research and travel awards.
Maybe we can move the community support fund to be supported by that
endowment. Maybe something around education, or maybe we can bring back
the newsletter. I don't know. But again, if you all are
percolating these thoughts and have any suggestions, please feel free to email me,
as again, this is what I'm going to be working on
over the next however many months/year.
And then just a little last slide here
is to remember that we now have a donate button on the website,
which is very fun. It's located in the top right of the header.
But if you would ever like to donate anything to TADWIG, you may do so.
And you can always
designate what you want that donation for, and it will be that way.
I will make sure of it.
That's all.
As long as nobody in the back tells her that just took 25 minutes, that would be
great. No, I'm just kidding. So as you can see,
we've got a lot going on with the treasury.
Chandra has been doing an excellent job of sort of bringing
us up into the appropriate decade.
And Stan Bloom, myself in particular, have been working with Chandra to
support those efforts. And so the executive can
expect some of these conversations to happen over the next year.
But if you have any suggestions, in particular about investments
that make sense for an organization like TADWIG, we would love to hear
that. So don't be a stranger and please share your
thoughts. That would be really excellent.
Elections are coming for us, not just in the United States, of course, but
for TADWIG.
A familiar slide. These are all of the folks who are currently
in seats right now and the roles that they fulfill.
But there are a couple of things that happen.
Every two years, essentially all of these seats, with the exception of the
deputy chair.
The deputy chair is elected, sits as deputy chair for two years,
and then moves into the chair position.
And so the
chair itself is not elected every two years.
It's a four-year thing. You're elected for four years.
Everything else is every two years.
As far as I can recall, we don't have any term limits on any of these seats,
with the exception of the deputy chair and chair.
And so some of these seats that will come open, I'll share with you in a moment,
some of the incumbents will probably run again, and others will not,
and that's okay. But elections are here for a reason.
They give our membership an opportunity to think about who they'd like to have
making decisions and
sharing what we do with the community.
And so what we've got coming up
are several positions.
The secretary position will be available at
the end of this year.
The role of the person who fulfills that seat
is responsible, of course, for things that you would expect.
It helps us to set up meeting minutes and organize those minutes, to maintain the
calendar, take notes when we have our executive meetings, which we do
twice a month, on the second and fourth
Tuesdays of every month.
Plus, there are other activities that if anybody's
interested in learning about the secretary role, I am happy to share
what I know, as would anybody else on the executive.
So feel free to inquire if you have questions about that role or
any other. The treasurer's position.
You have seen what Chandra has been up to the last couple of years.
I dare you to come up with better graphs and charts.
We have a couple of subcommittee chairs that are open.
The TAG chair is currently open right now, and we do thank Ben Norton for
filling that role for an extended period of time, and all of the work and the time
and the effort that he put into that role.
But he's got other fish to fry, and so we're looking to fill that
position,
maybe with one person and possibly maybe a
co-chair situation. So think about that possibility,
and let us know if you're interested in
that role. That's sort of the engine that drives TADWIG, that committee,
the Technical Architecture Group,
and we would love to talk to anybody who's keen to step
into that role.
Similarly, outreach and communications.
Javier currently sits in that role,
and has revived our socials among other types of correspondence,
communications with the community in a great way.
So if you're interested in that,
you just think about what we've been doing and take a look at that and
maybe come with some ideas of your own.
And I suspect, although I've not heard it officially, that Javier is not
planning to move his couch out of his office anytime soon.
So,
that would be a lovely opportunity perhaps,
either for Javier or for somebody else in the room.
We have a couple regional representative positions.
These are folks, the role of which is that you're intended
to give the executive an idea, a
bird's eye view of what's going on in that particular region, and
also to be able to turn that around and share with the region what
TADWIG is attempting to accomplish in a whole variety of ways.
And all of the stuff that we've been doing this week is a good example of
many of the things that we could share with those regions in various
ways.
There are some additional responsibilities.
Of course, you attend executive meetings,
but there are also some new things.
The community support fund
that we revived a couple years back.
The submissions that anybody, or the proposals that anybody
submits for an award go through the regional representatives.
It's their responsibility to review those and make recommendations to the
executive officers to say yay or nay to those
awards.
And for this batch, we're going to start
requesting that each regional representative be engaged in some
sort of outreach
or extension activity every year, whether that's
sharing a workshop in your region, whether it's being involved
in helping to organize,
taking a real role in organizing our spring meetings,
or in some other way,
that we're really trying to push our outreach
in meaningful ways, and especially into regions that
have traditionally been difficult for us to maintain.
Africa, Latin America in particular.
It's just difficult for us. And so if anybody has
suggestions about how we might, of course, continue to make inroads in
those areas, that would be great. But again, if anybody is
interested in joining us on the executive in any of those
areas,
that would be lovely.
This year,
the Asia rep, Daphne Ho, may or may not run
again.
Our Latin America rep, Juan, may or may not run again, and
North America representative, Eric Crimmel, may or may not run again.
I haven't had the time to sit down and have conversations with them, but
anyone is welcome to join the election.
That's how elections work. And it would be great to have
choices for people, for our membership to choose from.
Let's see. Is there anything else?
Does anybody have any questions about elections and how they run, or are there
members here that
have any thoughts?
That's a good thought.
You got to
push the button up.
Our question is, when do the nominations close?
That's a great question. It's Dan Bloom.
Yes.
So when does this all... I actually don't really know
Use the microphone. Let's say end of October. There you go.
And twist arms until then. Yes. We're good at twisting
arms in a way that doesn't leave marks. So, we can teach that to you if you need.
See? Works for Kit every time.
All right. Any other thoughts?
Okay. So,
as I mentioned in the opening ceremony, this is a great way to be involved.
If you're not ready for an election, those functional subcommittees are a great
opportunity.
I will add this about the functional subcommittees.
If you don't want to run for chair or a position that's elected, that's
perfectly fine, but those are the committees that we need you to join.
I would love to be able to show next year in Montreal a
list of people that are participating in each of those committees.
Kit needs help.
Javier needs help. Patricia needs help. The TAG needs support.
All of these groups can use more energy, more
ideas, more thoughts, and we would
welcome
your participation.
And so we will hear from our subcommittee chairs,
just a few minutes from each of you.
If you would prefer to stay down there, that would be fine.
If you would like to come up and feel magnificent up here at the
lectern, you are welcome to do that, too.
But we will start. Ben, if you are around.
I think Ben is around. If you want to come up, or
there is a microphone right there if you'd like to...
Ellie's got it.
Yeah.
And thank you, Ben, for doing this.
Yeah, sure. Is this the TAG one first? All right. Awesome.
I got a couple of these things. All right.
Yeah, Darwin Core data package ratified.
You guys know all this. BioBag of Terms.
We've done a lot of stuff this year. This is good.
And so if you're seeking a new TAG chair, if you're interested in it, if you want
to know about it, what the role does, what you're responsible for, all these kinds
of things, please let me know, or talk to David.
I'm happy to sort of run it through with you. It's a great role.
You get to do a lot of cool things, meet a lot of cool people.
So if you're interested in that, sure.
Actually, she'll talk about the accomplishments this year, but we had a really big
year. So this is good. Latimer Core is almost there. We have to change some stuff.
MIDS is going to public review, we think, next week.
So, it'll be a big thing. And Darwin Core data package finished their public
review,
too, this year actually. So it's really good.
So,
good.
Great. Thank you. Thank you, Ben.
So we have a lot of... Yes.
And as I mentioned earlier, Ben had to step down from his role.
He's got other responsibilities, other fish to fry, and we do thank him for,
was it four years? Five years?
17 years that you gave in the role, and we really appreciate all
your efforts. So thank you very much, Ben.
All right, Kit and the Time and Place committee.
Hello. Okay, perfect.
Hi, my name is Kit Lewers. I am the chair of the Time and
Place subcommittee. And boy, do I ever need help.
Anybody. Would love some help.
So next year's conference is going to be in Montreal, and as we know, last year was
in Colombia. But we are aggressively, and by we, I
mean me, would love for it to be a we sometime soon.
So please feel free to contact me.
Looking for 2028. So 2028 is the biggest priority, and I would
like to thank the people who have come up and talked to me during this conference
for 2028, 2029, and I believe 2030 locations.
So really appreciate that. But yeah, once again,
looking for members. You'll get to see my dog every meeting.
Trust me, he loves to jump up into the camera.
And I will send special Valentines to anybody who joins the Time and
Place committee. So yeah, that's it from me.
And thank you all for being here.
Thank you, Kit.
I would appreciate it very much if all of you would forget that you heard what is
in bullet item number one for at least-
Oh my God
... another 30 minutes. It's okay.
It's the worst-kept secret in biodiversity.
And I'm really sorry.
So, it's all good. I know you guys are...
If the strong mental power, I know you can resist your celebrations for
another 30 or 40 minutes.
Kit owes me a beer now.
All right. So Patricia,
fundraising and partnerships.
It's not working.
Oh, you have to use the clicker. Green button.
Oh.
So for the fundraising and
partnership committee,
we had a workshop in May,
and this year we concentrated more on the fundraising part.
So we had some brainstorming with very enthusiastic participants
on how we can support the executive committee.
What I didn't say is that we are all volunteers.
Nobody is paid, so we do that additionally to our work, and
sometimes it's a lot.
We also looked what are the needs in support for the
ratification and processes of the standards, the support
for the interest and task groups, and last but not least, how we can
support TDWG events, both for the organizers but also
grants for the participants.
Some of the first outcomes, so just discussion level.
Some in that meeting suggested if TDWG should not, like other
organization, work with a sort of umbrella association
for which for a bit of money we outsource the
financial and other administration
work, still supervising it, but having it done
by such an association like BHL or others are doing,
so that we can concentrate more on the
core business of TDWIIG. Nothing is decided.
It's just a suggestion from participant to that
workshop.
We also did lobbying with many funding agencies to
support TDWIIG activities. We need the help from everyone there.
And we also need more input from the regional representative
because there is some bias because of the
countries, for example, for me, Europe, that we know, but we really
need the help because we cannot know to be good balance all
the funding opportunities all over the world.
And then to conclude,
a decision that we took that might be a bit paradoxical is
that we decided to stop the TDWIIG European branch
because we had no capacity for the running project, and it was
hard to manage the staff, but also the other costs.
And maintaining this branch in Europe had also quite some cost,
and administration that was hard to follow.
So we decided on an alternative model as
of this year, where it's the TDWIIG main
headquarters in the US that can be associated partners to
EU project without funding. And we prefer the
funding to go to the EU institutional members who
then do the work, and we ask the coordinator or some
other institution to keep a bit money aside in other costs so that
we can participate and be invited to the meetings of these EU
projects. And an example is the recently submitted
Bicycle AI coordinated by Pensoft.
And we eagerly wait by end of this month or begin October to get the
good news if it's accepted. So let's cross finger, and then
we will have a really nice project for TDWIIG,
completely in the subject of this conference to test all these
nice AI tools. Thank you for your attention.
Thanks,
Patricia. All right. Thank you, Patricia.
One more. Javier, you ready?
Lucky last.
Lucky last, indeed.
One second.
All right, here we go. Do I change the slides with this?
Yep.
All right. Thanks.
So, thanks everybody for joining.
So let me try to keep it simple. Basically,
trying to work with outreach and communications for this year.
The goal was very simple and very humble, is trying to
resurrect our online presence. And I do apologize for all the
spamming this week. I trust things are going to slow down
from the next few minutes.
But essentially,
basically, this is part of what we did, and essentially,
it was trying to oil the machinery to start working again
because I think we needed to have a better presence, particularly
online. So most of the focus was on, precisely
communications. There is still some work to do in outreach.
But this is a summary of what
we have been working, and I say we because personally, it is more than
me doing this work. So,
we had a work plan precisely to say what we are going to focus.
Part of that plan is
what are the major activities that TDWIIG does year after year,
putting the conference apart, that it is a different animal.
So these are some of the activities that were mapped in that work plan.
Obviously, as you see, I am listing the conference on its own,
and also I had the opportunity precisely to reach out to our
partners networks to say, "Hey, can you help us spread the word?"
And also, we are more than happy to reciprocate.
And while our social networks probably needed some attention, I think we
are getting there.
So essentially, you saw that more recently
from the start of February, there were more regular updates, particularly on
our major social,
that is LinkedIn, but we have also Mastodon, Blue Sky and
Facebook. So also we
improved the staging publishing for the website.
While some of the pieces were there, I think it was more a
trial and error.
What else happened? So there are a few tools precisely that
we started to use incorporating our day-to-day work in
communications. So one is a short URL
service, certainly, and thanks
to Matt in particular, Matt Blizzard, to help me set up that.
Also as a non-for-profit, we have access
to a free professional license for Canva.
If you are into design, you know how handy it can be to have that
tool as opposed to only try to do everything using Paint or PowerPoint.
So we have that also under our belt in TDWIIG.
Also recently, we also integrated a tool precisely to be more civilized
managing social networks as opposed to manually manage every single
one.
And also taking experience from previous
colleagues, we have a communications brief.
While it hasn't been highly used, I think it proves to be handy when
preparing communications
for the standards in particular. So it is just prompting
whoever wants to put something out there is
What is the key message? Who I am.
Trying to say that the numbers doesn't look that big, but just having
35 social campaigns is no simple task
when that is your part-time job. So,
also adding to that, there were 25 separate emails, and I think
it is very careful. You don't want to be spamming on a mailing list
that often, so I think that's a good balance.
And also, probably our biggest social presence,
as I mentioned, is on LinkedIn. So that number is now
outdated and thanks to you guys. Starting
in the year, it was late January, we have around
160 followers on LinkedIn. That number, as of this
conference, is 1,285. Thanks for that.
So we continue growing, and that's a big number for TADWIG.
Yep. And again, we have here a few numbers,
most impressions for a single post.
Again, those are numbers that I have been learning myself,
but the call for abstracts for this conference is the one that was breaking record
for us with basically 10,000
plus impressions. So that is people that actually interacted with that
or were looking at that on their screen for, don't know how many seconds, 30
seconds or so.
So definitely, we are getting there. We are getting people's attention.
Yep. And well, the second-most,
well, post with the more impressions is the
communications about the Darwin Core ratification.
So, trust me, I'm almost there.
So particular, I really wanted to thank, because as I mentioned, this
is a collaborative effort. So particularly on the
technical side, Stan Bloom has been with me.
I don't know what time Stan sleeps, but-
... yeah, he was always there,
wanting to help. Yeah, Matt Liset, as I mentioned, he has been key,
precisely helping precisely with any technical support with all our
systems, and also Peter Desmet. We had good conversations,
particularly for the website.
In the communications, I put in here a few mentors, past colleagues
like April Suhn and more recently, Ian Deweer helping me
precisely with the basics about communications because, well, I don't have
to tell you that my experience prior to this was nil, but
I am there. And
second, basically what I call my partners in crime.
It was a pleasure to work with precisely Gigimer Stanersen,
precisely our mascot for the conference.
I think it was very useful, the different poses and so on, to make it
more amenable. Yes. Stan, as I was mentioning, also has been helping me
throughout this journey. And special thanks for our designer.
She couldn't make it here, but Rosivette Hernandez
needs a particular recognition precisely.
If you have seen all the templates for the conference, the one that we are using
here,
all the magic with all those designs, well, that was all Rosi.
Yes, and finally, apologies, but you will see the latest creation from Rosi.
But again, I am with you, Kit. We have a misfire also.
But anyway,
that's it. But you will know what I mean later.
One thing to mention, actually two things to add to what Javier shared.
And by the way, thank you. Javier's been kicking some butt,
doing comms, and that's great. I do want to acknowledge
Nikki Nicholson, who got us started on the path of Blue Sky
and a couple of those new platforms and sort of predated some
of the work that's happening most recently.
And so, if she's here somewhere, thank you, Nikki.
Appreciate that very much.
Also,
I'm going to call it out right now. Rosivette Hernandez,
is
the greatest person on the planet right now.
She produced all of the template, the PowerPoint templates, the
graphics, the
headers, the footers, all of that sort of stuff,
for the conference. And while we couldn't bring her here,
just definitely want to recognize her,
and all of her efforts over the last year or so on that project.
Working groups. So I want to say a couple of things.
So the
subcommittees are, of course, very core to what we do and how we work.
But the working groups, the maintenance groups, the interest groups, the task
groups, that's where the work gets done for TADWIG.
The technical architecture group and also the infrastructure group, to
some degree, work with all of these
task groups or
working groups in some way, shape, or form at some point in the process, whether
it's at the beginning or when it's just prior to ratification.
Everybody's involved in one way or another.
There's a lot of stuff happening with TADWIG right now, and it's exciting.
And there's some really great things coming down
in the near future.
One of the great things is that we now have received 19
working group reports.
So I hope you're willing to sit here as I give each of them five minutes.
Is that okay?
No.
Okay, I didn't think so. So,
we're going to
play this out a little bit differently.
So everybody named Ellie who is holding a microphone, could you please
raise your hand?
Okay. There we go. Both of them.
For
those working groups that have a representative here, I would like you,
if you wish, you don't have to, but you will feel the pressure to do so,
just to call out one thing from your report.
The coolest thing, the most exciting thing, the most important
thing that you've been working on over the last year, if that's entirely
possible. So we will not expect you to come up here so
that we're not- Losing walking time for all of that, for all
19 of those groups.
I will show you these reports that were submitted, but very
briefly. If you have any questions or would like to see these
reports, these reports satisfy the requirement, the annual requirement for
an annual report to the executive of the activities and future
intentions for each of these groups.
So these are not just presentations for your entertainment.
They are, in fact, important documents for us as we move forward.
So if anybody wants to see something in greater detail, just let me know.
But in the meantime, at random,
because who knows how to alphabetize at the end of a week like this,
we will just hit up each group,
and take a look at what they've got going.
Remember
just one thing.
Who's first?
So the MIDS Task Group.
Yes. Thanks, Dave. So if it's only one thing, then you can go to the next slide
immediately already.
And,
if that works. Can you-
Did we get it? Nope.
Yes.
So, Ben already stole my scoop, but the MIDS Task Group
will go under public review starting next week, so the date on that slide is
actually wrong. It's 28th of September, Monday next week,
not October, and it lasts for about two months.
And feel free to submit any feedback, comments, criticism,
anything to the GitHub issues or to a Google sheet, which we will then
share when the review formally opens.
And I think that is really the most important thing this year. Thank you.
Perfect. And we're a standards body, so who's interested in...
Who needs details
with the dates? We'll figure that out.
There will be announcements going out about that public review soon.
All right. GeoSchemes. Anybody here from GeoSchemes?
All right, so there are two, just so you know.
There's GeoSchemes Terrestrial, and then there's Marine, and I have
slides for both.
Okay. So just to tell you, Paco is leading this
terrestrial working group, and Serge Corfas and Nicolas Bailly are leading the
marine
schemes interest groups. So two things.
We are about to submit
our proposal for standards for both the terrestrial and
the marine. I don't know if you have the second. That's...
Okay. So that's it. So we are about to submit our proposal
for the standards for the executive committee.
We still have some pending questions, and we need guidance for that,
and maybe we can still ask Ben for some guidance about it.
And yeah, that's it.
Okay. Anything to say about the marine folks?
Right. We are at the same level for most.
Okay.
Mm-mm.
Perfect. Thank you.
All right.
Latimer Core.
Hi. Yeah. Thanks, Ben. On behalf of all the working groups,
thank you. You're getting us into places that we didn't think we could get.
The big thing for Latimer Core this year is that we've finally
worked with exec and tag and everybody else to figure out the
difference between structural, descriptive, and terms layer.
So that's what we're working on through this year.
Hopefully, beginning of 2027, we'll put that out
for public review, maybe earlier if we can.
But that's what we're doing.
Thank you, Sharon.
Oh, yeah. They're all wonderful. Thank you, people.
Darwin Core.
Steve's somewhere in South Africa having fun.
I'm not the convener, but I will be on the next round.
That's not the biggest thing. The biggest thing is actually something that
is probably the least known, and that is we will now, from the end of
this public review, go into scheduled public reviews on
specific dates during the year. And I'd like to know about a
calendar where that can be publicized, and then everybody will
know
I have to have my mature proposals ready
by November 1st or March 1st, or whatever it might be.
Excellent. Yeah. And that's an exciting thing.
The growth of Darwin Core and the Darwin Core DP has been significant over the last
couple of years, and there are so many thoughts and ideas and
suggestions of all stripes,
that we're going to have regular update phases
and review phases for that. So we'll get that on the calendar and let folks know,
send it out through socials and so forth.
So we'll talk about exactly when you want to have that happen, and we'll make
it so.
All right. IQ Air.
There's Yasin.
Thank you, Dave.
We just started this year, so we are so excited.
We are coming strong. We already have a few hundred
terms that we need to discuss, but we still
need other
use cases from other taxonomic groups, so you're all
invited to join
the task group. Especially if you are working with image
quality and AI,
we welcome your participation. Thank you.
Thanks, Yasin.
All right.
What do we got here? Machine Observations.
Peter's not able to be here,
so each of you pick a bullet point and read that.
Or one of those and read that.
Read it again.
Okay, perfect. Mineralogy. Ben's over here
We're done?
No.
We
need to hear for the recording.
You have to say that so that
people know.
You can yell it into the microphone now.
We finished. We finished ours up. So,
35 terms. We had a whole bunch of people.
The last-- We're done. It's great. So, it'll be out.
It's just the exact last one. I know I did fancy slides.
I feel like the kid from the class nobody likes because they just do what the
teacher says, but it's okay. So,
these are all the people that helped.
The left-hand side are all the people in the task group.
We had a community review that predated the public review in Darwin Core for just
people in geosciences community.
Part of the effort of the mineralogy extension was to bring more people from the
geosciences community into TDWG, and part of that was getting people to
look at the standard ahead of time.
Because we know most people are biologists, and we want to make sure we're on the
right track and don't want to do things silly.
So, all those folks on the right reviewed it ahead of time.
And then, of course, John, thank you for all your help in this process.
And Erica Criminal, too, who couldn't be here today, but she did a lot of stuff,
too.
Awesome.
Good.
Perfect. Thank you.
Realm and Biomes. Anybody here from Realm and Biome?
Okay.
Those are three easy ones. Thank you,
Celia,
Pierre, Kate,
and John.
ABCD.
Most important thing is we have now improved documentation already
last year, but it
wasn't reported last time.
Yeah. Okay. And that's it. It will further improve, it's not done yet, but now
we have term for term documentation with all of the details.
Excellent. Thank you.
Are you ready for all of them?
Yep. There you go.
No, that's the one. Let's skip that one.
Oh, yeah, that's-
Yeah.
That's my other task group. So,
for the standards mapping,
yeah, we've met a couple of times, and it's
really likely, we haven't decided it formally yet, but the recommendation
will be that that wave mapping should be done in Triple
SOM or the CSOM, as some like to pronounce it.
I've seen it pop up a couple of times during the different talks.
If I have not talked to you and you are working with Triple
SOM and are not part of the group, please get in contact
with me. I would like to, yeah, discuss this a bit more.
And so we are, next year, hopefully giving out the recommendation.
And then also, next important part is how to
present the mappings in a user-friendly way.
So, how to generate
nice web pages or things like that.
There are some standards already doing that, so that's a really great basis to work
off.
Yeah. And come to the meetings.
I will announce the upcoming meetings soon. Yeah.
Thank you.
All right. Just in case you
weren't sure if TDWG was doing a lot,
there's a lot going on. Lots of different types of standards, lots of
extensions.
Not just the ones that you hear about every day. Lots of things are going on.
Let's see, BDQ.
All right.
There's Lee.
One thing, Lee.
Yeah.
What? Oh, one thing.
The best thing.
Paul Morris, John Wychorak, Arthur, and myself are looking
forward to a Christmas present this year.
Perfect.
That will do.
That'll do. I like it.
Sensitive Species.
Not here. Okay.
They're doing things.
All right. TCS Maintenance, there we go.
I feel like there's a convener bias in this room.
Thank you.
Well, our big thing is that the TCS2 was ratified
at the end of last year,
which elevates TCS to a current
TDWG standard. And,
once we're done basking in our glory,
our next activities will all be about making it work,
and we would like to get some more people involved.
Perfect. And just in case anybody was curious, glory lasts
a long time at TDWG, so basking happens, and it's a good thing.
All right. What have we got? Invasive Species.
You guys were busy this weekend for sure.
Okay. So, just before this TDWG meeting, we had our first
physical task group meeting, thanks to the Community Support Fund.
It was great.
The output was that we will suggest four new
properties to add to the Darwin Core Data Package, and
we are focusing on a few new vocabularies.
But the main conclusion was that the Darwin Core Data Package
held strong, and there just needs to be a few tweaks to
include Invasive Species management data.
Excellent. Thank you.
Modeling.
Okay.
All the slides.
Thank you. That was 19 of them. Didn't feel like it, but we appreciate
all of the work all of those people that are doing
right now. It's really excellent stuff, and we hope next year that we'll
have even more to report to you. So,
again, if you're interested in joining any of these efforts,
you can contact the conveners that were listed on these slides, any of the folks
who spoke or anybody in the executive, and we can direct you to the right people.
So anybody's welcome in any of these groups.
You don't need to be an expert. You just need to be interested
So Deb, where are you? There you are.
So, unfortunately, we lost one of our community
a couple of months ago,
and we want to take a few minutes
for a bit of remembrance of Henry.
Deb is going to come up and say a few words.
We will have the opportunity if you wish to say something,
you may do so.
And
we will make sure that these statements and/or
the book that Deb will talk about, make it to his family
in an appropriate timeframe. Thank you.
I'm going to
do this-
Yes
... while you're talking.
Cool. Henry, please come up here with me.
Quentin. What?
Thanks. Sorry.
Henry, please come up here with me.
I'm not Henry.
I know.
That's Henry.
I know. So,
first of all, I'd like to say thank you to everyone who took the time to share
thoughts in here, and I'd encourage you to do so if you knew Henry.
And we'll share this with his family and his partner.
His family and his partner are online with us at the moment,
and we'd love to take these moments to
bring our perspective about the Henry we knew and love
with his family. And with that, you get to see some of the history, and
I would like to say a few words from my perspective.
And Quentin's going to jump in.
So I know Henry from both the SPNHC world, the Society for the
Preservation of Natural History Collections, and the TADWIG world.
He is one of these members that bridges the communities in the
most wonderful way.
Henry, I miss you. I miss your laugh.
I miss your witty and your wicked sense of humor, and of course, a
dance partner.
Of Henry, who I miss, you were loving, kind,
generous, adventurous, and grounded.
We share our love of both TADWIG and SPNHC and the humans
in this community.
Your sharp insights, keeping the work that needs to be
done grounded
in those who are doing the work and the needs that they have, keeping
it real for all of us.
We also shared our love for singing, dancing, travel, food,
ceramics, and so much more.
Henry is that family member that you want to hang out with.
Someone who makes you feel better simply by being with them.
Henry, I miss you, and may your spirit stay with us always.
Thank you.
Yeah, I shared an office with Henry for many years, and
he always grounded me in reality with my mad ideas.
But many of you won't know Henry and have never met him, but he
exemplifies the community of TADWIG, of the
inclusiveness of a diverse community interested in many
different things. But beyond everything, just a passion for
biodiversity and for making a difference in the world and making the world a better
place. And, yeah, wherever you are, Henry, at the moment,
I hope you're contributing somehow in TADWIG at least.
We feel your spirit here. So, thank you, Henry.
Is there anybody who would also
like to say a word or two?
Have a witty anecdote or a silly story?
And should you perhaps not want to share here, but you would like to
record something, you can always send a recording to me.
I will make sure it gets to the people it needs to get to.
And we also have a book that has been on the registration table for the last
several days that you're welcome to sign.
Deb will have it available and open as long as there are people here.
And somehow, this one sort of represents Henry in all of his
facets.
I can stand up here all day.
It's okay.
Anything else you'd like to say, Deb?
Yeah, Sharon, please.
There's already information about the
stuff that happened in gardens that we share this
year.
For those of you who
maybe don't know Henry, he was absolutely one of those people that just
hung on to you. He found you and was there.
And I
think I'm right in saying, Quentin, you might know, that the
gardens at Mesa are going to have something
like a tree planting or something, I heard.
I don't know if you want to mention that. No? Okay.
So if anyone has any extra pictures,
I know
this kind of came together
maybe in a little vacuum, but if you have any pictures to share,
please get them through to Deb or anyone that's
stood up here, because we want to make a kind of nice album.
It'd be fun to see. He was a fun guy. He would love this.
That's all
Yeah. We have a folder
filled with images. This is just a selection.
So if you have images and you want to send them to me or to anybody on the exec, we
can add them to that folder as well and then send them on.
Thank you.
Yeah. You're welcome.
Yep.
Thank you, everybody, and thank you to everybody who has signed the book so far.
Thank you for making space, Valerie. We appreciate it.
Yeah.
All right. Deep breath.
And now for something completely different.
So for many years, we've had a student award
that we've given out, often for
public speaking or for an oral presentation, sometimes for a poster.
It's been a little hit-or-miss, but this year we've decided that we've officially
named that award the Pensoft Student Awards. There are two.
There is one for best poster and one for best oral presentation.
And so this year, this is what our judges were looking
for.
And in fact, they did find it, which is great.
And the prize is from Pensoft in both cases,
and that's a complimentary publication in a Pensoft journal.
So
that's
amazing, especially if you're a student.
That's a great boon
for your
progression in the world.
There were six posters this year, 18 oral presentations.
There were five judges
that did their best to find those best and
review those
presentations and posters.
And so if any of those folks are in the room, are any of you here?
All fled town.
Okay. Well, we thank the judges. We also thank Chandra, who I do
know has left already for the airport, for putting that together and
organizing that with Pensoft, which is great.
And so we won't delay.
So for the first award, before we get into that,
would you like to come on up and ...
Thank you very much. I don't know if you would like to say anything on behalf of
Pensoft before we get going, and then I
will announce the winner.
Well, what I would like to say is that the philosophy of life is
such that some members of our communities
are going, but some others are coming.
So, let me congratulate the
forthcoming generation of biodiversity informaticians,
awarding
two young scientists, early career researchers.
And the first one is
Claudia
Campanini.
Is Claudia here?
Thank you.
Thank you, Claudia.
So if you'd like to get a picture of you guys.
Oh. Okay.
Sure.
Thank you.
Congratulations.
All right. And the second award
for best oral presentation
is
Yesheng Qiu.
Is Yesheng here?
Yesheng might not be here-
No. Maybe he left, yeah
... at the moment, but we will make sure that
they get their award.
Someone from the same country, same institute here, like
Yesheng?
Okay, we-
Come on up here for a second.
Maybe I didn't pronounce the name right.
Maybe you can tell us how to pronounce it.
Qiu. Okay.
Qiu. Yesheng. So we both learned something.
Yesheng Qiu, yeah.
Yeah. Thank you.
So, yeah, on behalf of Yesheng.
Yeah.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Thank you very much. We'll do this again next year.
All right. So that's great.
BioBlitz, who's been taking pictures of things, identifying things?
That's good. You don't have to be bashful.
So this is what we've done so far. The BioBlitzes, both the international
and the local
BioBlitzes, will continue for another week.
And so far,
there is a clear
winner in the most observations category, both in terms of
local and
international. Vijay is doing this in India because that's where he
lives.
Some great species identified, and we encourage you to keep that up.
We'll keep doing this for another week, so have at it.
And then a couple more things.
This would be a good time to alert anybody that's downstairs to
come up if they are still here.
But before we even get into that, just some things that have happened
and places we've been, just to remember you by
Wow, that was pretty cool.
I don't know about you, but I like that space.
And by the way, if I can get a copy of taxonomic backbone,
I will make T-shirts available next year.
People will buy those. So wherever that came from,
ALA people, get me a copy of that
image.
Good stuff. There were two marriages, both same-sex marriages.
Neither of them lasted more than 35 seconds.
But it's a step forward for TADWIG. It's good.
Oh, yeah. Where's that one?
Yeah, the one over on the far right.
This is evidence that John Vachark is now not the only person that
knows that I'm actually a hobbit.
By the way, this picture on the right, just so you know, rare occurrence in
the forest.
One current and seven past chairs were present all
at the same meeting. I don't know if that will ever happen again.
I hope it does, but that was pretty cool.
And waterfowl, of course.
Lots of waterfowl.
By the way, if you didn't make it to game night,
ha.
We dined
on Argentinian chocolate
and a custom bespoke whiskey,
among other things.
A dozen games were there, and we played,
well, just about to about 11:30.
So thank you to the
museum and the botanical folks, Natural History Museum and the Botanical
Museum for hosting us.
Who went on the river walk?
It's a cool event.
You can be forgiven for skipping game night for that.
Now before I move on,
some folks you should know. Of course, first again,
Roosevelt Hernandez, thank you so much for all of the graphic
design work that you did.
Organizing committee folks,
will you please stand one more time so we know who you are?
It's a game of attrition planning a meeting like this.
There are only six of them standing.
But the amount of work that goes into organizing a meeting like this is
tremendous. Literally have been working on this, we've been working on this
for 18 months.
We started meeting at least once a week,
a year ago, approximately.
And that's two meetings every time we meet, one for the east folks and one
for the west folks. So people, this is a global adventure
in the way it works. And so the organizing committee, thank you so much for this.
Our hosts
at the Biodiversity Services at the
University of Oslo, at the Natural History Museum, at GBIF
Norway,
thank them, please, one more time.
I think it was a great meeting. I don't know about you.
Despite how tired I am, it was still a great meeting, and I hope you
all met some good folks, met some old friends, and had lots of really
great discussions.
Is there anybody I'm forgetting?
That's kind of how much noise is in my brain at the moment, too.
All right. Oh, are any of the volunteers here?
Did they make it up? One volunteer, yes.
So on behalf of TADWIG,
to you, and you will have to share this with every volunteer, but
Dog, you can also, Kathy, who is not here also,
you guys were awesome.
Manning the tables, the registration, keeping food going, making sure
people could find the bathrooms,
all of the above.
Stellar effort, and we can't thank you enough, so.
Why don't we do this one more time?
Next year. Someplace else, though.
So
now you can remember what Kit said
30 minutes ago,
and we have a little video to play.
We'll go ahead and get started.
All right. There we have that.
The video compression did a little number there at the beginning, but
that's all right. It's the end of the week. Kind of all feel that way.
I will add one thing. This is coming together really fast.
And some of the stuff we just don't seem to have much control over
sometimes.
But this is going to be in June next year. Okay?
So please note that. Please also note that is a Wednesday through Saturday,
because those are the only dates available in the great city of
Montreal. So please note both of those, the slightly different
situation. Please also note,
additional partners, GBIF will be there, OBIS
will be a part of this, and Canadensys, and there will be additional
partners that we'll be naming in the months to come.
So it's going to be big.
We expect perhaps 800, 900 people,
and a lot of good food
in Montreal.
So we hope we'll see you there.
And if not you, perhaps some of your colleagues instead.
That's pretty much the good news, and that's the end of the meeting.
So I congratulate you on making it. I thank you for attending.
It was great to see everyone,
and I hope you have safe travels back to wherever you are headed.
Thanks very much, everybody.
So those remaining living members of the organizing committee, if you could
come up so we could get a picture up here, that would be great.
And members of the executive committee, too.
Okay.